<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober word to a serious people: or, A moderate discourse respecting as well the Seekers, (so called) as the present churches. Wherein the difference between them touching visible administrations, is discovered and discussed: and may serve as a plea for the nations ministery. / By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>Jackson, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J78A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097810</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097810</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171394)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2572:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober word to a serious people: or, A moderate discourse respecting as well the Seekers, (so called) as the present churches. Wherein the difference between them touching visible administrations, is discovered and discussed: and may serve as a plea for the nations ministery. / By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>Jackson, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Cottrel for James Noell, in Foster-lane; and are to be sold by Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-Eagle neer the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Jackson by Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 61 numbered as 63.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Seekers (Sect) --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171394:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOBER WORD To A SERIOUS PEOPLE: Or, A MODERATE DISCOURSE RESPECTING As well <hi>The SEEKERS,</hi> (ſo called) As <hi>The Preſent Churches.</hi> Wherein the Difference between them touching Viſible Adminiſtrations, is Diſcovered and Diſcuſſed: And may ſerve as <hi>A Plea for the Nations Miniſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a lover of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 22.30.</hi>
                  </bibl> A ſeed ſhall ſerve him: it ſhall be counted to the Lord for a generation. <bibl>
                     <hi>24. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> This is the generation of them that <hi>ſeek</hi> him, that <hi>ſeek</hi> thy face, O Jacob. <bibl>
                     <hi>14 7.</hi>
                  </bibl> Oh that the ſalvation of Iſrael were come out of Sion! When the Lord bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth back the capivity of his people, Jacob ſhall rejoyce, and Iſrael ſhall be glad.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Cottrel,</hi> for <hi>James Noell,</hi> in Foſter-line; and are to be fold by <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle neer the Weſt-end of Pauls. 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171394:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171394:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou art here preſented with a brief Diſcourſe touching a Subject which hath not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to <hi>commend</hi> it ſelf, and therefore ſubjects it ſelf to thy Ingenuity and Candor in its peruſal, (if it be thought by thee worthy thereof.) To invite or court thee thereunto, would be very unbeſeeming thee to whom it's directed, conſidering thee both <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;</hi> and to me it's no leſs unſutable, if thou kneweſt my Genius. Thou art therfore left free, either to entertain it, or paſs it by, as thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt; and it's as freely ſubmitted to thy Cenſure.</p>
            <p>But conſidering it's poſſible that ſome may beſtow time upon it, for their ſakes I have been
<pb facs="tcp:171394:3"/>
prevailed with to ſay a little by way of Preface, touching the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>end</hi> thereof, both which when thou clearly underſtandeſt, thou wilt with the leſs prejudice attempt the reading and examining of it, when it ſhall be freed in thy judgement from ſuch aſperſions as ſome may raſhly (yet too plentifully) beſtow upon it.</p>
            <p>Be thou therefore hereby aſſured, that thou art not troubled with this Diſcourſe out of any deſigne either to weaken thy preſent confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which thou haſt in God, or to ſtartle thee touching thy preſent Practice in things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, nor out of any Irreligious, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical, or Self-ended intereſt, to tempt thee to caſt off all Ordinances of Worſhip and Service of God, which thou at preſent art perſwaded thou oughtſt to be found exerciſed in; but to give thee an account touching a Sort of people which ſome are pleaſed to call SEEKERS; of whom, ſeveral men, in ſeveral books, have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſeveral things, ſhewing the dangerouſneſs of their Opinion, and the dreadfulneſs of its tendency; and under that term of <hi>Seekers,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all thoſe which differ from themſelves touching the preſent exerciſe of Viſible Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations. How great their miſtake hath been
<pb facs="tcp:171394:3"/>
and is, thou mayſt finde herein; the rectifying whereof, is one End of this Work, by laying down ſomewhat poſitively touching what they believe and practiſe, and ſomewhat privatively touching ſuch things as they ſee not ground to practiſe. Theſe are reduced and abridged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two Heads, The
<list>
                  <item>Preſent Churches,</item>
                  <item>and Preſent Miniſtery,</item>
               </list>
and compared with the Primitive Patterns of each, as they are laid down in the Scriptures, and accordingly applied, with ſome Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations had touching certain Objections de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereupon. Under which general Heads, thou haſt the ſum of what thou wilt here be troubled with, (and perhaps thou mayſt judge it worthy thy trouble.)</p>
            <p>As touching the End, to give thee ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as well what it is, as what it is not, be pleaſed to know, that having obſerved many perſons of an enquiring ſpirit unſatisfied with their preſent Practice, as not ſeeing ſufficient ground for it; yet impatient and reſtleſs in their ſpirits, have made out after this people (ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed as before:) but finding them very
<pb facs="tcp:171394:4"/>
inconſiderable both for quantity and quality, and nothing extant which in any meaſure might be a ſtay to them, by laying a ground for their dependance &amp; further waiting upon God, have waxed weary, and almoſt fainted in their minds, and at the beſt have returned to that condition from whence at firſt they thought themſelves happie they were eſcaped, uſing ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as theſe: <hi>Come, let us go back to</hi> Egypt <hi>for Bread: it's better take it at the mouth of Ravens, then ſtarve.</hi> Which expreſſions have been very ſadly uttered by ſome: mean while, the God which had led them by the hand out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and brought them thorow the <hi>Red-ſea,</hi> cannot be truſted, nor depended on, nor waited for, while they are in the wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, on their part, have moved me to bethink me of my duty to my God, and whether I were not obliged, in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to him, who had betruſted me with the knowledge of his pleaſure in any meaſure touching this particular, to impart it to others, that they might alſo have the opportunity of conſidering what hath been a ſtay to my own ſpirit, and perhaps may prove forcible to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent from further ſtraying ſuch who are upon rhe like enquiry.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:171394:4"/>I have likewiſe obſerved how much it hath offended and grieved divers good perſons who are themſelves under the practice and exerciſe of ſuch Adminiſtrations as this Diſcourſe treats of, becauſe the SEEKER'S (as they are called) do not joyn iſſue in the practiſe thereof; expreſſing this offence and trouble of theirs, by writing and otherwiſe; which I have great cauſe to hope will by this occaſion be abated, or at leaſt moderated, when they ſhall perceive that there is a reaſon to be rendered for that which they have judged unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>In the conſideration of which, I cannot but think it's poſſible that Thou, <hi>Reader,</hi> mayſt finde thy ſelf to have drunk too deep of the cup of my former, and thy preſent Errour, in that both thou and I have taken up our Practices upon other mens Principles, or at leaſt upon too eaſie &amp; too ſlight a ſearch; touching which, if they were to begin again, we ſhould judge it neceſſary to put a pauſe, and to make more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent enquiry after the minde of God in the Scriptures. To which ſome perſons are reduced, (and that in mercy) ſearching and ſeeking after thoſe things <hi>now,</hi> which long ſince they preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med they had attained. To the exerciſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:171394:5"/>
thou art alſo invited, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove thy own works, that ſo <hi>thy rejoycing may be in thy ſelf, and not in another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if, in examining this Work, thou findeſt many things weak and amiſs, I ſhall not wonder at it (I pretend not to Perfection:) Put thy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter upon them, &amp; let them paſs for droſs, and write them <hi>mine.</hi> But if thou findeſt Gold (I mean Truth) that will abide the fire of trial; ſay that's God's; 'tis none of mine; and let not that paſs. I expect thy Cenſure; I ſhall hearken for it: and I hope thy Reproofs ſhall be as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as the ſmiting of the <hi>righteous</hi> was to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 141.5: and for ought thou knoweſt, if thou ſendeſt me back to the ſearching of the Scriptures, which muſt be the Standard &amp; Rule of trial, I may truly be enabled to ſay, <hi>It ſhall be a kindneſs to me, an excellent oil which ſhal not break my head.</hi> But if thou ſhalt be found <hi>reproaching</hi> in ſtead of <hi>reproving,</hi> and <hi>wounding</hi> in ſtead of <hi>ſmiting,</hi> I hope my God will teach me to ſay, as he did alſo, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth, and keep the door of my lips.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> thou art deſired to correct theſe <hi>Errata</hi> with thy Pen.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. lin. 37. for 26. 5, read 46. 5. p. ibid. l. 17. adde <hi>the.</hi> p. 5. l. 1. for <hi>theſe,</hi> read <hi>the.</hi> p. 7. l. 31. for <hi>certain numbers,</hi> read <hi>a certain number.</hi> p. 20. l. 12. for <hi>caſt,</hi> r. <hi>coſt.</hi> p. 25. l. 9. for 12. 8. r. 21. 8. p. ibid. l. 33. for <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> r. <hi>Tranſlators.</hi> p. 33. l. 2. for <hi>perſon,</hi> r. <hi>perſons.</hi> p. 36. l. 7. for <hi>had,</hi> r. <hi>was.</hi> p. 39. l. 12. adde <hi>of.</hi> p. 47. l. 24. for 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. r. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. p. 48. l. 15, for <hi>particular,</hi> r. <hi>peculiar.</hi> p. 57. l. 25. for 10. 25. r. 11. 25.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171394:5"/>
            <head>A SOBER WORD TO A SERIOUS PEOPLE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt thoſe many Diſcourſes which have offered themſelves to Publike View, in theſe diſcourſing Times, there have not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral that have aſſerted the Saints pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in their enjoyment of Ordinances; Some Moderately, Others more Smartly, and with leſs Moderation, (though with no leſs Confidence.) The Entertainment theſe Diſcourſes have met with (I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) hath been as various.</p>
            <p>That which I have obſerved in them, is, that they have frequently taken notice of ſome that differ from them, calling them <hi>Seekers:</hi> Touching whom, many things are ſaid, by way of Anſwer to ſeveral Objections which are ſaid to be theirs; though it be not ſo demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable from any thing yet extant, which they (if any ſuch there be) have owned as theirs. Nevertheleſs, in the ſerious peruſal of thoſe very Objections, and their ſeveral Anſwers, which are exhibited to Publike view, there doth ſeem to lie ſomething not ſo clear, on the Anſwerers part, as is imagined, and as were to be wiſhed.</p>
            <p>To ſhew, in all things, where this Shortneſs doth (ſeem at leaſt to) lie, would require more time then is alotted to me, in reſpect of other employments: I ſhall therefore abbreviate many things, and,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171394:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as briefly as I can, ſhall endeavour to ſhew where I have obſerved the main difference to be placed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seekers,</hi> I do finde, are charged with this, That they are a people who deny all Ordinances; and the Evil of that Evil is laid down and aggravated, by ſeveral Perſons, in ſeveral Books; and in the laſt, moſt of all.</p>
            <p>Theſe are again diſtinguiſhed into ſuch as are <hi>againſt</hi> all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or that ſee not ſufficient ground for the preſent practice of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; or ſuch as are <hi>above</hi> and beyond Ordinances.</p>
            <p>For the former, thoſe which are againſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> contrary to them, they are very <hi>improperly</hi> called <hi>Seekers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the later, they which are above and beyond them; theſe are ſo far from <hi>Seeking,</hi> that they are rather Poſſeſſors, Enjoyers, and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers, then Seekers, properly ſo called.</p>
            <p>The third ſort are ſuch, as, not ſeeing a ſufficient ground for the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Ordinances, are ſaid to ſeek them. And is it not their Mercy, that moſt High ſhould give them a heart to ſeek him, for wiſdom, and counſel, and directions, touching thoſe things they ſee not ſufficient ground for the preſent practiſe of? And is it not according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's Rule? <hi>If any man want wiſdom,</hi> he ſhould <hi>ask,</hi> or ſeek it, <hi>of God; who giveth liberally, and upbraideth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a good ſence, it is a good thing to be a Seeker: In a bad ſence, it's not to be applied to them, which ſeek the Lord in ſincerity, for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, how to walk before him.</p>
            <p>Of this ſort of Perſons, and this ſort of Seeking, this preſent Diſcourſe onely treats.</p>
            <p>And touching them, it may be obſerved, that theſe (<hi>Seekers</hi> ſo called) are not alike unſatisfied concerning the practiſe of all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. There are onely ſome, wherein they ſee not ſufficient ground for their preſent practiſe. There are others, which they themſelves do practiſe: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, They believe, that it is an appointment from the Lord Jeſus, and that wherein they ought to excerciſe themſelves, in ſearching the Teſtimonies of the Holy Writings of Truth, concerning the minde of God touching things to be believed and practiſed: So did the Eunuch, and God met him therein, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.28. to the 25. according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They judge the ſame touching Prayer, and diſtributing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171394:6"/>
to the neceſſity of thoſe that want; according to <hi>Act.</hi> 10.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hoping to enjoy God, both in the former and latter duties and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of his.</p>
            <p>This is not onely practiſed perſonally, and privately, but, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offers, by coming together into ſome place on the Firſt-dayes, and at other times, as their hearts are drawn forth, and opportunity is offered.</p>
            <p>Their ends in ſo doing, and grounds for ſo doing, are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they may be Inſtruments in the hand of the Lord, to ſtir up the grace of God in one another, by mutual conference, and communication of experiences: according to <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That they may poure out their complaints to the God and Father of Spirits, for the further revelation of himſelf: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4, 16, 17, 20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p>Thridly, That they may keep alive, and hold out in their meaſure their witneſs and teſtimony againſt the falſe, and waite for the manifeſtation of the true Lord Jeſus, in his pure Ordinances of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and Worſhip: according to <hi>Daniel</hi> 3.16, 17, 18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137, thorowout.</p>
            <p>Expreſſing their deep ſence of the want of what they enjoy not, behaving themſelves as perſons having neither power or gift to go one before another, by way of Eminency or Authority; but as Sheep unfolded, and as Souldiers unrallied, waiting for a time of gathering, and reſtitution to the knowledge of what as yet they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not: and the attainment of this, is the end of their ſeeking; and to this they ſtirre up and provoke one another; and herein they deſire to be found, hoping firmely to the end: according to the firſt of <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p>Owning nor acknowledging no other viſibe Teacher, but the Word and Works of God; on whom they wait for the Grace which is to be brought at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt. By which it doth appear, that though they come not up to the full of what others ſay they enjoy, in reſpect of Miniſtery, and Worſhip; yet they are not againſt them, or beyond, or above them: But comparing ſuch as ſay they are, and have ſuch, by the Scriptures of Truth declare themſelves to be <hi>deſirers</hi> (though not <hi>diſcerners</hi>) of them. Such who though they cannot ſay they ſing the Songs of <hi>Sion,</hi> yet do hang
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171394:7"/>
their Harpes upon the Willowes, and weep at the remembrance of her; to ſee how like a Plowed field ſhe lies, and how her Stones lie covered over with Rubbiſh.</p>
            <p>Thoſe other Ordinances, wherein they do not ſee ſufficient ground for their Practice, may be comprehended in theſe two: The preſent Churches, and the preſent Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Theſe two were the Grand, and Capital, and Comprehenſive Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and appointments of the Lord Jeſus; unto which, He gave gifts, for the perfecting of the Saints: But whether the preſent Miniſtery, and the preſent Churches, be thoſe Ordinances of His, which He then inſtituted and appointed, and not rather ſomething like them, or inſtead of them, is the matter in Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The perſons called by the name of <hi>Seekers,</hi> having compared them with the Word of God, and not finding them to conform there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, dare not joyne iſſue in the preſent practice of them: which of it ſelf is ground ſufficient: yet that it may appear that this ground and reaſon is not without Reaſon, ſomewhat is to be added, by way of Demonſtration and Evidence.</p>
            <p>There have not been wanting thoſe which have taken paines to prove the Affirmative, and to reprove the Negative ſharply: It's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to conſider of thoſe proofes ſeriouſly, and endeavour to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoſe reproofes as profitably as may be; to ſtate the matter in queſtion as fairely, and truely, as the preſent Capacity is abilitated, and can extend to.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I finde it's moſt generally taken for granted, that Diſciples, <hi>quâ</hi> Diſciples, or, as others ſay, Diſciples able to preach the Goſpel, have power, and are commanded to Baptize, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. and upon this ground it's practiſed; and this is all the Miniſtery that I can finde is acknowledged by ſome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Believers may incorporate themſelves, and become a Church, is by others affirmed, from <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. That being made ſons by believing, they have <hi>power to become the ſons of God</hi> in ſtate; which, I ſuppoſe, is meant, that Believers have power to eſtate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into viſible Sonſhip; or elſe I know not what to make of the diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Others expreſs the ſame thing with other words, much different; proving a Church, and Miniſtery, upon other Principles and Grounds.</p>
            <p>From all which, as I differ in the Matter, ſo I ſhall in the Method;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171394:7"/>
deſiring to lay down ſomething Poſitively, from theſe Scriptures; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the judgement and cenſure thereof: judging it moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, rather then to take notice of the ſeveral Objections I have ſeen, with the Anſwers to them: Knowing well, that Truth is truely evidencing and convincing: and if this ſhall approve it ſelf ſo, it will ſave labour of anſwering thoſe Objections; though ſomething will be ſpoken to them alſo, in their place.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who himſelf was the Great Apoſtle of his Father, as well as <hi>the High-prieſt of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> Heb. 3.1, whilſt he was to perform his Father's work,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.8</note> whoſe Meſſenger or Apoſtle he was, as being ſet apart and ſent forth for that purpoſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.38, 39, 40. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.49. <hi>and ſpake and acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commandment he had received from the Father:</hi> In the performance of which Miniſtration or Service, he was pleaſed <hi>to ſingle out ſome certain perſons from amongſt others,</hi> whom he appointed and authorized to wait upon him in that Miniſtration or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Thoſe he termed <hi>Diſciples,</hi> or Apoſtles. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.1, <hi>When he had called to him his Diſciples, he gave them power,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now the names of the twelve Apoſtles were theſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe twelve Jeſus ſent forth, and commanded them, ſaying, Go not into the way of the Gentiles; but go rather to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael: and as ye go, preach;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Verſ. 16. <hi>Behold, I ſend you forth,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe twelve were ſuch as he <hi>ordained from amongſt others.</hi> Mar. 3.13, <hi>He went up into a mountain, and called to him whom he would, and they came unto him. And he ordained twelve, that they ſhould be with him, and that he might ſend them forth to preach.</hi> Luke 6.13, <hi>And when it was day, he called to him his Diſciples, and of them he choſe twelve, whom he alſo named A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> Theſe Diſciples were not meerly ſuch as were followers of Chriſt, and had learnt of him, as Scholars; but ſuch as himſelf, <hi>out of others,</hi> had Choſen, Called, and Ordained, that they ſhould be with him, and that he might ſend them forth to preach; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he did, and named them <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. and <hi>Luke</hi> 6. doth evidence. And what Commiſſion he had, the ſame he gave to them. As he ſaith of himſelf, <hi>I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael:</hi> ſo he commanded them not to go to the Gentiles, nor into the way of Samaria; but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171394:8"/>Beſides theſe, he likewiſe ſent forth the Seventy, with like Power and Commiſſion to preach the Goſpel, and to confirm it by Miracles, as Himſelf and the Apoſtles alſo did. But in a more eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did the Twelve converſe with him, upon all occaſions, as his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual attendants, or houſhold-ſervants. During the time of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration upon earth, and when he was about to finiſh the work which the Father ſent him to do; ſo far as concerned his perſonal preſence, he delegated that power the Father had committed to him, into the hands of them, thoſe very perſons whom before he had ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be with him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>Now the time approaching wherein the Moſaical Diſpenſation was to expire, and the Chriſtian Church and its Worſhips to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced in the ſtead thereof, our Lord Jeſus (having fulfilled all righteouſneſs as touching the Law) gives commandment that the Goſpel be preached to <hi>all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the perſons to whom Chriſt did delegate the power and authority of Preaching and Baptizing, much is written, as hath been hinted before.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, To Believers, as Believers.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, To Diſciples, as Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, To Preaching Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, To Diſciples able to preach the Goſpel, ſo as to bring over ſouls to believe and be baptized.</p>
            <p>Others ſpeak in other expreſſions. It is too much to follow them in all.</p>
            <p>There be four things I ſhall deſire may be enquired into; the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion whereof, will take in moſt of the Scripture which any way give light to the underſtanding of this Subject; and which may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally anſwer many Objections which otherwiſe require particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar diſcuſſion. I ſhall propound them by way of Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Whether Chriſt did not commit the Preaching of the Word, and adminiſtration of Baptiſme, to a Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, What the nature and end of that Miniſtery was, which the Lord Jeſus appointed to ſucceed him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Whether there be any pattern of any viſible Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church under the Goſpel, without or before a Miniſtery or Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171394:8"/>Fourthly, Whether the preſent Miniſtery, and preſent Churches,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> may be acknowledged the Miniſters and Churches of Chriſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the firſt Pattern.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe:</p>
            <p>That Power and Authority, to Preach and Baptize, was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Apoſtels, or to the Eleven Diſciples, as to a Miniſtery, might be demonſtrated,</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the Equity of it; which appears in the Reſpect or Care which the moſt High was pleaſed to manifeſt in the firſt order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or diſpoſing of the Adminiſtrations of the Jewiſh Church; which he committed to the hands of ſome choſen and peculiar perſons, diſtinguiſhed from others of the people to whom the like power was not committed; as to <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1, 2. And by then ſignal of his diſpleaſure manifeſted againſt thoſe who would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it <hi>Num.</hi> 1 6. but confederated in the Conſpiracy of <hi>Korah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Lord took ſuch care to ſet in order, and keep right that houſe whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> had the management, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Jewiſh Church, (and therefore called <hi>Moſes</hi> his Houſe) and to eſtabliſh its Miniſtery; is it not as equal that the Lord Jeſus ſhould take the like care for his Houſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Chriſtian Church, and provide for its Miniſtery; and that as the former, ſo the later, ſhould conſiſt of perſons peculiarly ſet apart and appointed thereunto?</p>
            <p>This ſort of reaſoning from the Old to the New, and from the Former to the Latter Diſpenſations, the Apoſtle doth uſe, by way of Equity, many times, to prove the matter whereabouts he was reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Doth God take care for Oxen?</hi> If ſo, then it is as equal, at leaſt, that he ſhould take care for ſuch as labour, and tread out the Corn under the Goſpel. But if this have not weight enough to prove the matter in queſtion; Secondly, it may be evidenced from Scriptures that are direct, as to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That it was committed to certaine numbers of perſons, who, from among many others, were appointed and ſet apart for this work, appeares from the Scriptures afore mentioned, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. He called to him <hi>whom he would,</hi> and they came unto him, <hi>and he ordained twelve,</hi> that they might be with him, and that he might ſend them forth to preach: of them which came unto him, he ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed twelve And ſomewhat more plain doth <hi>Luke</hi> relate this action, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.13, <hi>He called to him his Diſciples, and of them he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171394:9"/>
choſe twelve; whom alſo he named Apoſtles,</hi> or Meſſengers, or men ſent out. Now though this ſeeme to relate to them onely as to Preaching, yet it is to be conſidered, that to theſe very ſame indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual perſons (thus choſen, and called, and ſet apart from others) was the Commiſſion given to Preach and Baptize, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.16, 18, 19. <hi>The eleven Diſciples went away into</hi> Galilee, <hi>and Jeſus came and ſpake unto them, ſaying,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.41, 42, <hi>Not to all the people, but unto Witneſſes choſen before of God, even to us: and he commanded us to Preach unto the people,</hi> &amp;c. Now that they were ordained and appointed to ſerve as a Miniſtery, it appears from the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> the ſecond Verſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with verſ. 17 and 25. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil the day in which he was taken up, after that he through the Spirit had given commandment to the Apoſtles whom he had choſen.</hi> And in verſ. 17, ſpeaking of <hi>Judas,</hi> (ſaith) <hi>He was numbred with us, and had obtained part of this Miniſtery.</hi> And in verſ. 25, it is ſaid of <hi>Matthias, That he may take part of this Miniſtery and Apostleſhip, from which Judas by tranſgreſſion fell away. And the lot fell upon Matthias, and he was numbred with the eleven Apoſtles,</hi> or Meſſengers, or men who were ſent out to preach, and baptize the Nations.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond:</p>
            <p>What the nature of that Miniſtery was which the Lord Jeſus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſucceed him in this ſervice.</p>
            <p>Beſides what hath been ſpoken already, the Scripture doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what plentiful proviſion the Lord of the Harveſt, made in point of a Miniſtery. In <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13, you have the Goſpel-Miniſtery expreſſed, both in their Names and Numbers, their Nature and End, in reference to their Uſe and Duration in the ſame Order and Degree which the God of Order hath placed them in.</p>
            <p>For their Name and Number, the reading of the eleventh Verſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares both.</p>
            <p>For their nature and uſe, it's laid down either more generally, in this term, <hi>for the work of the Miniſtery;</hi> or more particularly, in theſe two Termes, <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For the edifying the body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The duration of this Miniſtery, was to be till we all came to the Unity of the Faith; even all this whole Miniſtery, ſo numbered, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171394:9"/>
named as before; who were all, as well as any, the fruit of Chriſt's Aſcenſion.</p>
            <p>The Gifts given to men for the work of the Miniſtery, thoſe were to abide (as to Inſtitution) one as well as another, one as long as another, the one without the other not being perfect; as in another caſe it's ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. As theſe were given to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue till we all came to the Unity of the Faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13, ſo they were ſet in the Churches by Ordinance and eſtabliſhment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, as that which was to continue.</p>
            <p>But to return to the nature and uſe of this Miniſtery; <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To perfect the Saints.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To edifie the body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Word which is here uſed, <hi>To perfect the Saints;</hi> will be read properly, <hi>to perfect</hi> the number <hi>of the Saints,</hi> as well as their graces; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ad coagmentationem Sanctorum,</hi> verſ. 12.—until there be not one Saint or Elect more to be added to the number. It comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quod propriè de numero dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> Or from the the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perfectum reddo, vel omnibus numeris abſolutum reddere.</hi> The Tranſlators have rendered it ſeverally in ſeveral places, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> to prepare, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5, <hi>A body haſt thou prepared me.</hi> Rom. 9.22, <hi>Adapta ad interitum: Fitted to deſtruction.</hi> To reſtore or put in joint: <hi>Luxata membra in locum reſtituere;</hi> And ſo it is uſed in <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1, <hi>Ye which are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titual, reſtore ſuch a one with the ſpirit of meekneſs.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10, <hi>Be ye perfectly knit together in the ſame minde. Sitis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacti, vel coadunati.</hi> If ſome one member of a true Church ſhould be overtaken with a fault, and in that ſence be out of joint, the reſt which are ſpiritual ſhould reſtore, <hi>i. e.</hi> put ſuch a bone in joint againe. But if many members ſhould do the like, and the whole prove diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and disjointed, Who ſhall reſtore them to their former order againe, but the hand of that Miniſtery by which they were adapted, and fitted, and firſt knit together? For, they were not onely given for this end, that they might <hi>perfect the</hi> number of the <hi>Saints,</hi> by fitting and preparing them, and puting them in joynt; and this act rendered as tranſient, to paſs away in the very acting, or once doing: but they are ſaid to be <hi>ſet</hi> in the Church, <hi>i. e. ſtatuit, aut determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit,</hi> the word is of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, <hi>Statuo in Sione lapidem; Behold I lay,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſet,</hi> or <hi>appoint</hi> by an irrevocable decree, <hi>in</hi> Sion <hi>a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171394:10"/>
chiefe corner-ſtone.</hi> Act. 13.47, <hi>Conſtituite,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I have ſet</hi> or appointed <hi>thee to be a light to the Gentiles.</hi> Act. 1.7, <hi>It is not for you to know the times or the ſeaſons which the Father hath put in his own power.</hi> Now theſe are not tranſient, but abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding things: ſo the Miniſtery, which is for <hi>the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> in the ſence above expreſſed, was in like nature not onely given for that end, but fixed and eſtabliſhed <hi>by appointment</hi> for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The other branch of this Miniſtery was, <hi>To edifie the body of Chriſt, and to build upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chiefe corner-ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to apply what hath been ſpoken to the Miniſtery which Chriſt gave for this work, as it conſiſts of two branches, <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perfecting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edifying.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe workes are appropriate to two parts of the Miniſtery: The firſt are called Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts; and precede the Church,<note place="margin">Matth. 28.19. Mat 16.15 Epheſ. 2.20, 21, 22.</note> or are before it, having the whole world for their Circuit, dealing with them as with the World, with the Nations as with the Nations; Diſcipling them, preparing and fitting them; felling, hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſquaring thoſe ſtones and that timber, that it might be made meet for the building; as alſo laying the foundation, even themſelves, next and in order to the Lord Jeſus, acknowledging him to be <hi>the chiefe corner-ſtone</hi> of the building, and the building it ſelf to be Gods, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9, 10, but themſelves labourers therein, and wiſe Maſter-builders thereon.</p>
            <p>The ſecond are ſuch as being part of the number of thoſe which have been ſo gathered out of the World, and placed into the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the former Maſter-builders, and by them alſo appointed to edifie the body, <hi>i. e.</hi> to carry on the building, keeping to the foundation; furniſhing them with Rule, and Square, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and Line, and Plummet, and whatever was neceſſary to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat this work, or make the Man of God perfect. All which are comprehended in the holy Scriptures, and more collectively in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Miniſtery are called Paſtors and Teachers who are to feed the Church, as the former were to breed it; theſe to carry on the building, as the other to lay the foundation; theſe to be reſident
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171394:10"/>
where they were choſen, as thoſe to paſs on, and prepare, and fit more materials for the perfecting of the great building, the whole Houſe of God.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as the number of the Saints are to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and then to be edified, and this to be done by a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, conſiſting of Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers; and foraſmuch as this is made the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ſo named and numbered as before, to be accompliſht not by any one without the other of them; not by the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles alone, or Prophets onely, or Evangeliſts onely; much leſſe by the Miniſtery of Paſtors and Teachers onely: but by theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as making up the Miniſtery which Chriſt aſcending on high gave, and by Ordinance or appointment ſet and conſtituted in the Church. <hi>And</hi> ſeeing the number of the Saints is not perfected, but rather, as that Scripture ſaith, <hi>The whole world lieth in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or in that wicked one, and that there are ſtill Nations, and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds, and Tongues, and People to whom the Goſpel may be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and amongſt whom Diſciples may be made, and Churches formed and built upon the true foundation: Hence I conclude with my ſelf (and refer it to the judgment of him that reads it) in anſwer to the Queſtion, That the Miniſtery which the Lord Jeſus appointed to ſucceed him, was for nature and end a breeding and feeding Miniſtery: The one, to prepare the Saints, and to gather them into a Church, as will be endeavoured to be proved in its proper place; the other, to build on upon the firſt foundation, being firſt gathered and ſet thereon.</p>
            <p>And that theſe are both alike for their end and duration or continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, appeares,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe they together make up but one Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe they all being the fruits of one Purchaſe, the ſame neceſſity remains for the one as for the other: ſo long as any Saints are to be gathered, as well as any to be edified, theſe are to continue; and that is, <hi>till we all come to the unity of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c. the Elect of God ſtanding in as much need of the one, inſtrumentally to enlighten and convert them, as of the other, to edifie and ſtrengthen them, being converted. For as God, when he gave one, gave the other alſo; ſo the Saints may ſee a neceſſity for the continuation of the one, as well as of the other: the former, namely, Apoſtles, Prophets,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171394:11"/>
Evangeliſts, having been ſome ſpace of time without the later, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. but the later, I conceive, have never been in truth without the former, (at leaſt, I know not where, or when, and ſhould be willing to be informed) foraſmuch as the Foundation muſt precede the building up of the Superſtructure; and the Paſtoral feeding the Lambs of the Lord Jeſus, muſt needs preſuppoſe a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Breeding to have preceded, in thoſe pure and orderly Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The third and fourth Queſtions I ſhall anſwer together.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>Whether there be any Pattern of any Viſible congregated Church under the Goſpel, without or before a Miniſtery or Baptiſm: Or, Whether the preſent Miniſtery, or preſent Churches, may be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Miniſtery and Churches of Chriſt, according to the firſt Pattern.</p>
            <p>To the firſt part of the Queſtion, this will be anſwered:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>That it doth not appear in Scripture, that any of the firſt Churches were gathered into their Viſible Order, without a Miniſtery preceding or before Baptiſm. If it be otherwiſe, it's hoped it will be ſhewed where and when. If it be not to be ſhewed, How deeply are they concerned, who ſet up ſuch Churches, whereof there is no Pattern in the Word of God!</p>
            <p>I know it is ordinarily ſaid, and accordingly practiſed, that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Believers may, by mutual conſent or agreement, become a Church, and appoint one to baptize the reſt; and accordingly chuſe their own Officers, and proceed to other Adminiſtrations; and this in the Name of Chriſt. And ſuch a Company of Believers are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, by themſelves and ſome others, a true Viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Others ſay the ſame thing, in other words.</p>
            <p>Now I would argue the caſe a little touching Believers conſenting to become a Church, ſo far as may help to clear the Queſtion in hand.</p>
            <p>When a perſon deſires to joyn himſelf to ſome one of the preſent Churches, though the perſon be never ſo deſirous in himſelf to be added, yet he can but propound his deſire of joyning and being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. This Church conſiders and judges of this perſon's Faith, and fitneſs for Fellowſhip, and that in the Name of the Lord; and muſt declare the Lord's conſent, in the Church's, to the receiving ſuch a Perſon into ſuch a Fellowſhip, before he can be admitted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171394:11"/>The perſon's willingneſs in himſelf to be joyned, makes him not a Member of ſuch a Fellowſhip; he cannot give his own conſent, and the Church's too: but as he is willing to manifeſt his readineſs to be admitted; ſo the Church judging of his profeſſion of Faith, and fitneſs, manifeſts her conſent, by receiving him in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, either by Baptiſm, or without, according as they have faith in that Particular; I mean that Fellowſhip or Society which ſo admits him.</p>
            <p>Now if this be the Method or Ordinary way of proceeding in a Church after it is gathered, Is not the gathering of that Church, in its firſt beginning, to be ſuppoſed equivalent hereunto; foraſmuch as the ſame relation wherein one ſingle believer doth ſtand with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to a true Church rightly conſtituted, ſo do a Company of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſtand in relation to Chriſt, in their firſt congregating into the Viſible Order of a Church-eſtate:</p>
            <p>Which may be thus demonſtrated:</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the <hi>Bridegroom;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is the <hi>Bride, the Lamb's wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A company of Believers are ſuppoſed to be made willing, by the power of Light and Love, to be married to Chriſt, and to put on that Conjugal-Yoke of viſible Churchſhip, wherein they may manifeſt their obedience to him, ſubjecting themſelves to ſuch Ordinances and Appointments of his, as are commanded touching that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>But to whom ſhall they make manifeſt this their willingneſs? Who ſhall ſupply the room of the Bridegroom? Or who is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom's friend, that can Miniſterially declare Chriſt's acceptance of theſe Believers to become his Church, his Wife, and he to become their Bridegroom, their Husband, their Lord, their Law-giver; giving them power to ſit upon Thrones for him, to open and ſhut a door for him, to binde and to looſe in his Name and Power?</p>
            <p>Believers, I conceive, can no more in this caſe give their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents and Chriſt's too, then a particular believer that would be joyned to a Viſible Church, can give his own conſent and the Churches too.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as the true Church doth Miniſterially contain in her ſelf the ſtate of power to binde and looſe, to open and ſhut, in Chriſt's Name, to ſignifie his conſent, and in his Name to receive or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the perſon who pretends to, or aſſays to be joyned to her: ſo is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171394:12"/>
it ſeriouſly to be conſidered, who did at firſt Miniſterially ſupply the room of the Bridegroom, who did at firſt judge of theſe Believers fitneſs, or who did in Chriſt's Name accept of them, as they do in Chriſt's Name accept of others that deſire to joyn to them.</p>
            <p>That the true Viſible Church is the Spouſe, the Bride, the Wife of the Lord Jeſus, theſe Scriptures, among others, witneſs: <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9.</p>
            <p>That the conſent between Chriſt and his Church, at firſt, was acted Miniſterially, by ſuch as himſelf had deſigned for that purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to accept of the believers conſent on their part, and to eſpouſe them to Chriſt; and that this was effected by that Miniſtery which was wont to precede and go before the Church and its feeding Miniſtery, appears from the conſideration of theſe Scriptures: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus have I begotten you through the Goſpel.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.29. <hi>We pray you in Chriſt's ſtead, be ye reconciled to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this Miniſtery was thus inſtrumental towards their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal converſion, ſo was it alſo touching their Viſible Admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Eſpouſed, <hi>i. e.</hi> Church-eſtate: For not onely did they in Chriſt's ſtead beſeech them to be reconciled to God, but alſo did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, being ſo reconciled. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth touching the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that he did <hi>eſpouſe</hi> that Church <hi>to one husband, that he might preſent it a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt.</hi> And of the Churches of <hi>Macedonia</hi> it is ſaid, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. that they <hi>gave their own ſelves firſt unto the Lord and unto us by the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that this Diſcourſe intends, is but to put perſons (whoſe ſpirits can bear it) upon the conſideration how they became a Church at firſt, And whether that the practice of the preſent Churches doth not juſtly occaſion that enquiry; foraſmuch as the reaſon is the ſame, that the firſt Beginners of a Church have as much neceſſity of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons Miniſterially deputed by Chriſt to try and to accept of them, as well as for them afterwards to try, and judge, and accept of others in the Name and Authority of Chriſt, who deſire to be added to them.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of which, may ſerve for Anſwer to that part of the Queſtion, which concerns the preſent Churches:</p>
            <p>That foraſmuch as it is not demonſtrable that the preſent Churches
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171394:12"/>
have been ſo conſtituted by perſons Miniſterially deputed on Chriſt's part, to whom they might give up themſelves Viſibly (as well as unto the Lord) and by whom they might Viſibly and Miniſterially have the Lord's conſent manifeſted to them, (as they themſelves now mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it to thoſe which would be added to them;) but that they reckon it ſufficient to be made free and willing in themſelves, and without any Viſible or Miniſterial Authority to try and judge one another, and to accept of one another in Chriſt's Name and ſtead, and ſo become a Church, contrary to their own after-practice towards others; Seems to be altogether without preſident from the Word of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, are not to be acknowledged for the true Viſible conſtituted Churches of Chriſt according to the Primitive Pattern.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond branch of the Queſtion touching the preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Whether they are to be acknowledged the Miniſtery of Chriſt according to the firſt Pattern;</p>
            <p>Beſides what hath been ſpoken already, it may be further added,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That a Miniſtery of Jeſus Chriſt may be conſidered Immediately or Mediately ſuch; either as coming of that Apoſtolical Race who had their call immediately from Chriſt, as the firſt Meſſengers had, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.16, 18, 19, <hi>&amp;c. Gal.</hi> 1.1, 12, <hi>Paul an Apoſtle,</hi> (or a Meſſenger, or a man ſent out,) <hi>not of men neither by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe in the Scriptures are properly called Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, <hi>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for a man to be a Miniſter of Chriſt in this ſence, requires to have an immediate call and ſending forth, with gifts ſutable to ſuch a Miniſtery: <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15, 20, <hi>Go ye forth into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to every Creature. And they went forth and preached everywhere, the Lord working with them, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the word with ſignes following.</hi> Act. 1.4 5, 8, <hi>And being aſſembled with them,</hi> (i.e. <hi>the Apoſtles whom he had choſen,</hi> Verſ. 2.) <hi>commanded them that they ſhould not depart from</hi> Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>but wait for the promiſe of the Father,</hi> Verſ. 4. For, <hi>ye ſhall be Baptized with the holy Spirit not many dayes hence.</hi> Verſ. 5, <hi>Ye ſhall receive power after that the holy Spirit is come upon you, and ye ſhall be Witneſſes unto me,</hi> &amp;c. Verſ. 8. Which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed on God's part; for they did receive the promiſe of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171394:13"/>
the Father, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, and did perform their part, in the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent part of the Chapter and Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.23 Act. 6.3, 5, 6, 8, 10. Tit. 1.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a Miniſtery of Chriſt which is not ſo immediate, but more mediate; and they were ſuch, as whom the Apoſtles, in the behalf, and by the ſuffrage or the election of the Churches, did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain; and to whom they did delegate the power and authority of Jeſus Chriſt, for the work of the Miniſtery in the Churches: And in his Name and power, ſuch gifts were beſtowed as might fit thoſe perſons for the work whereunto they were choſen and ordained, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p>Theſe, though it be not to be denied but they are to be accounted the Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they are indeed his by appointment and inſtitution; yet they are ſuch more mediately, and the Churches more immediately; whoſe alſo they are, and out of whom, and for whoſe ſake, they were immediately choſen and appointed, while the other Miniſtery were to travel abroad, and to fulfill their Miniſtery towards the World; for which work they were Commiſſioned, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Go ye into all the World, and preach the Goſpel to every creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſtinction is grounded upon theſe Scriptures: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi> 2 Cor. 8.23, <hi>If any enquire of</hi> theſe, <hi>they are the Apoſtles of the Churches,</hi> or, as we have it tranſlated, <hi>they are the Meſſengers of the Churches, and the Glory of Chriſt.</hi> Philip. 2.25, <hi>I ſuppoſe it neceſſary to ſend to you</hi> Epaphroditus <hi>my brother, but your Apoſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a perſon do entitle himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, he muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf to be ſo, under one of theſe two conſiderations.</p>
            <p>If he be one of the firſt ſort, his Call muſt be immediate, (from the Bridegroom the Lord Jeſus) and his gifts and qualifications muſt be ſutable to his work; a powerful enabling to go forth to the World.</p>
            <p>If he be one of the later ſort, his Call muſt be from the Bridegroom's friends, the Apoſtles, or an Apoſtolical Miniſtery, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 14 of the ſame Chapter: <hi>When</hi> the Apoſtles Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Paul—<hi>Verſ.</hi> 23, <hi>when they,</hi> i. e. the Apoſtles, <hi>had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them Elders in every Church.</hi> Tit. 1.5, <hi>For this cauſe I left thee in</hi> Cret, <hi>that thou ſhouldſt ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordaine Elders in every City, as I had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171394:13"/>
thee.</hi> Or elſe the call of this later ſort muſt be from the Bride her ſelf, in whoſe cuſtody was left the power of all Adminiſtrations: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>I praiſe you, brethren, that you keep the Ordinances as I delivered them to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſutable to this Call (whether it be by the Bridegroom's friends or by the Bride her ſelf) muſt be the gifts beſtowed.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Paul</hi> do lay hands on <hi>Timothy,</hi> and ſeparate him to the work of the Miniſtery, the Lord confers upon him, thereby, ſome gift which he had not before, and ſuch a gift to which he is to give attendance. <hi>Wherefore I put thee in remembrance that thou ſtir up the gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.6.</p>
            <p>If the Church by her Presbytery (for ſo ſome will have that place to be underſtood) do lay hands on <hi>Timothy,</hi> it is not an empty and bare Ceremony, but ſuch an action as wherein God appears; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring by way of gift ſomewhat which was not before: and this likewiſe is to be attended to. <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Prophecie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Miniſtery of theſe times being compared and conſidered, will appear neither called nor qualified according to the Primitive Patterns.</p>
            <p>Friends of the Bridegroom in the firſt ſence, they are not, as being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent out from him with an Apoſtolical Miſſion or Embaſſage, furniſhed to wooe and win the Nations, to repreſent the perſon of the Bridegroom, and to be as in his ſtead, beſeeching men to be friends with God, intreating them to be reconciled to him. Their want of the heavenly Furniture of power from on high for this work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, doth evidence the truth hereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Nor are they called and ſent out by the friends of the Bridegroom; either by Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, or Prophets, who had their Call and Miſſion from Chriſt: Foraſmuch as they acknowledge no ſuch Miniſtery now extant, but ſay it was temporary, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary; though it be not demonſtrable from Scripture, when the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail was cut off, or ſuch a Miniſtery to ceaſe, according to deſignation or appointment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Nor is it ſo evident as it is imagined, that they have a true Viſible Call from the Bride her ſelf, a true Viſible Conſtituted Church of Chriſt, who hath been her ſelf firſt eſpouſed to him viſibly and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterially,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171394:14"/>
by ſome perſon or perſons hereunto deputed and deſigned, as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. according to the firſt eſtabliſhed viſible Order (by Faith and Baptiſm.)</p>
            <p>But from a Company of well-minded people, who, reading the Scriptures, and obſerving what is ſpoken touching the Miniſtery its uſefulneſs and neceſſity, judge it alſo neceſſary, lawful, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to chuſe out from among themſelves, or others, ſome ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as they beſt approve of, to go before them, and adminiſter to them; and this is accounted a true Call to the Miniſtery. Whereas it would be firſt enquired, Where the Scripture doth in any place give power to a people, how holy, how godly ſoever, to give a true viſible Call to the Miniſtery; themſelves not firſt being viſibly and Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially a conſtituted Church of Chriſt, and ſo his Spouſe, his Wife, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Primitive Pattern. Whoſe power, how far it extends, after ſhe is eſpouſed, I diſpute not; but ſeriouſly enquire after the actions of power which are performed by any people, before they are viſibly eſpouſed, and conſequently impowered thereunto.</p>
            <p>Hence I conceive it is, that this being practiſed, (the one giving, the other accepting the Call of the Miniſtery, without queſtioning the Power of either) it may without offence be ſaid, that a Powerleſs People give Call to a Giftleſs Miniſtery, (for, as they have not power, ſo they confer not any;) who, for lack of Gifts, ſtudy to acquire Arts; wherein alſo having attained, they therein exerciſe themſelves, (the wiſdom of God ſuffering it to be ſo) that they ſhould ſtyle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Maſters of Arts.</hi> But <hi>in the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> For when the <hi>gifts of God</hi> could not be bought nor ſold, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not appropriated to the gain or profit of the Poſſeſſor; then muſt Humane Arts be invented, (which darken the Sun and the Air) and the gifts of God exploded, and called <hi>extraordinary,</hi> becauſe they too much reſemble the heavenly Manna of old, a food which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved too dry for the growing intereſt of that time: which the moſt High beholding, withheld, and ſuffered not that bleſſed and heavenly dew to fall; But contrariwiſe, ſuffered them to grow drunk with Wine, to erre in Viſion, to ſtumble in Judgement, to ſurfeit of (their Quails) their Humane Arts of their own inventing, under which they have laboured many hundred yeers, fulfilling that Scripture, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.7, 8. and ſo it may be, until the time, the full time, is come, that that great Angel ſhall yet once again enlighten the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:171394:14"/>
18.1. and the <hi>ancient Goſpel</hi> be preacht again to <hi>kindreds, nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, tongues, and people,</hi> Rev. 14.6. Rev. 10. <hi>ult.</hi> Then may we expect and hope, that this Artificial Miniſtery, and its Artificial Teaching, the moſt High will <hi>conſume with the breath of his mouth, and with the brightneſs of his coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The zeal of the Lord</hi> can <hi>perform this:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 37.32. Iſa. 28.16. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note> onely <hi>he that believeth maketh not haſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection</hi> 1. Chriſt gave his Commiſſion to his Diſciples, in the name of Diſciples; intimating, that they, as ſuch, might both preach and baptize, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Diſpciles of Chriſt did baptize before they were called and ſent out, even while they were Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.22, 24. even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>John</hi> was caſt into priſon; and many of the Diſciples were not ſo much as called then, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.12, 18, 21. Therefore, Diſciples, as Diſciples may baptize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> What hath been already alleadged in this caſe,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> might ſuffice for anſwer to the firſt branch of this Objection; eſpecially, if there be added this Conſideration:</p>
            <p>That the nature of their Employment, at the time when Chriſt was to leave the world and them, was far different from what it had been all the while he had been with them: For, with reſpect to the Lord Jeſus, whoſe they were, and whom they ſerved, ſo long as he was with them in the fleſh, they were his Diſciples and Scholars: but now he was to go away from them, and to delegate his power to them, which the Father had given unto him after his Reſurrection: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. <hi>All power is given me in heaven and earth: Go ye therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.18, <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the world even ſo have I ſent them into the world.</hi> They were to be left Miniſterially in his ſtead, 2 Cor. 5.20, <hi>We, in Chriſt's ſtead, beſeech you to be reconciled to God.</hi> Now they were no longer to be reckoned Diſciples or Scholars, but Teachers, Inſtructers, <hi>Maſter-builders,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.10. And therefore, with reſpect to Chriſt, though they might be called Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo long as he was with them; yet with reſpect to the Power and Commiſſion given unto them by Chriſt, they were called Apoſtles, by way of diſtinction from other Diſciples or Believers. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.2, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42, their Doctrine was called <hi>The Apoſtles doctrine:</hi> and their Miniſtery was not called Diſcipleſhip, but <hi>Apoſtleſhip, Act.</hi> 1.24, 25, 26.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171394:15"/>To the ſecond branch of this Objection, That the Diſciples of Chriſt did baptize before they were called Apoſtles, or ſent out to preach:</p>
            <p>Firſt, I anſwer, that it's not ſo ſafe concluding from a conſequence, as that becauſe <hi>Matthew</hi> relates a paſſage touching <hi>John</hi>'s being put into priſon, before he mentions the calling of the Diſciples or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that therefore they were not called till after <hi>John</hi> was in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and conſequently did baptize before they were Apoſtles: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it's very apparent, the Evangeliſts do not obſerve the ſame method or order in the placing and relating the Hiſtories of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; ſome putting that before, which another puts after: which hath caſt no ſmall trouble to thoſe who have attempted to Harmonize the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Admit it be as it is objected, and that they did Baptize while they were Diſciples, the Baptiſme is not reckoned theirs, but Chriſts: It's ſaid <hi>he made and baptized more diſciples then John, Joh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.22. He baptized Authoritatively, they Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally: He made and baptized.</p>
            <p>He that Miniſterially doth baptize another by vertue of Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to him given, hath likewiſe Power and Authority to judge of the fitneſs of the perſon whom he baptizeth: ſo did <hi>John</hi> by thoſe whom he baptized, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. So did <hi>Philip</hi> by the Eunuch, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. So did <hi>Peter</hi> by <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Friends, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.46, 47, 48; by whoſe Commiſſion, at leaſt, if not by his hand, they were baptized. So here the Diſciples were ſaid to baptize, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4, but Jeſus was with them: Joh. 3.22, <hi>After theſe things came Jeſus and his Diſciples into the Land of Judea, and there he tarried with them, and baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The perſons then which were baptized by his Authority and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, he being with them while they were baptized, muſt needs have their fitneſs for admittance to be judged of by him, and ſo the Baptiſm muſt be ſaid to be his: He may be ſaid to baptize, becauſe 'twas done in his preſence, and by his Authority; they onely have this ſhare in the Work, that they are uſed Inſtrumentally to do that which their Lord and Maſter did Authoritively.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If it may be granted (as I ſuppoſe it may not) that the Diſciples did Baptize, in the fourth of <hi>John,</hi> by Warrant and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from Chriſt, given to them apart from himſelf; yet I ſuppoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171394:15"/>
their example therein is not to be drawn into practice by believers now, foraſmuch as Chriſt himſelf was a member of the Jewiſh Church both living and dying, (as it may be eaſily proved, if deſired) and a Miniſter of that Church: <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8, <hi>Now I ſay, that Ieſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion for the truth of God, to confirme the promiſes made unto the Fathers.</hi> So were his Diſciples likewiſe members of the ſame Church, and ſubſervient to their Lord and Maſter in that Miniſtration; as hath been proved at large in the former part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now what Chriſt did perform among them by himſelf, or by his Diſciples Miniſterially, would not be Warrant to theſe Gentiles for their Practice of the ſame, had he not after his Reſurrection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Power from on high, given Power and Command to the Apoſtles to teach the Nations whatſoever he had Commanded them.<note place="margin">Matth. 8.19, 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now unleſs it can be ſhewed, where and when the Lord Jeſus, or the Apoſtles, did ever teach Believers, or Diſciples, as Diſciples, to Baptize one another, ſince his Reſurrection and his taking poſſeſſion of all Power to himſelf, and commanding the Apoſtles to deliver that to the Gentiles to be by them obſerved, which he had formerly taught the Diſciples to obſerve themſelves: I ſay, unleſs it can be found in Precept or Practice ſince that time, I conceive the former Practice of the Diſciples, in the fourth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> (if it were every way as the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſpeaks) baptizing the members of their own Church, in the preſence and by the Authority of their Lord, he being the Miniſter of the Circumciſion for the Truth of God; will not prove a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground for the Practice of ſuch Diſciples, as is pleaded for by this Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Diſciples that are able to Preach the Goſpel, may Baptize,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2.</note> as appears by the Practice of the ſcattered Diſciples upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of <hi>Stephen,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and in <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19, 20, <hi>Now they that were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecution which aroſe about Stephen, travelled as far as Phenice, and Cyprus, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, preaching the Word to none but to the Iews onely.</hi> Doth not this give ſufficient ground for gifted men, if able to Preach, that they may Baptize alſo?</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer to the laſt branch of this Objection firſt.</p>
            <p>Gifted men,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> as they are generally underſtood to be of parts
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171394:16"/>
and abilities; theſe, without a true Power and Authority, may not by vertue of their gifts Baptize: For it is not to be doubted but there were many gifted men among the followers of Chriſt, when he gave to his eleven Diſciples Commiſſion to Teach and Baptize the Nations. For we read of the ſeventy Diſciples, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16, how that Chriſt ſent them forth to Preach, and what ſucceſs they returned with, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17, 18 19, 20. Yet to none of theſe, but to the eleven onely, was the Command of Teaching and Baptizing the Nations given, ſo far as appears to us in the Scripture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. Therefore neither believers onely, nor gifted men, though able to preach to the caſting down Sathan like Lightning from Heaven,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.18, 19.</note> without a true and lawful Authority, Appointing, and Deſigning to this Work, may warrantably do it.</p>
            <p>To the other branch, That Diſciples able to Preach the Goſpel may Baptize, from <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1, 12. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I diſtinguiſh between Preaching, and Publiſhing or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: Foraſmuch as though he that doth Preach, doth Publiſh the thing he Preacheth; yet one may publiſh a thing which he may not be ſaid to Preach, as will appear by this familiar example:</p>
            <p>An Herauld, or Crier, who is inveſted with Authority to declare or publiſh ſome buſineſs at ſome publike place, he muſt be underſtood to expreſs himſelf by words, to utter and ſpeak the thing he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes or proclaimes: there may be at the ſame time many a perſon preſent, who hearing and underſtanding the matter ſo proclaimed, may divulge and repeat what they have both heard and ſeen; and ſo may be ſaid truely to declare, but not to proclaim the thing: though the former in proclaiming the matter, uſed utterance and expreſſion; yet the later by uttering and expreſſing the matter, are not Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of it <hi>authoritatè,</hi> but obſervers, and relaters onely of what they have ſeen and heard.</p>
            <p>Let this circumlocution be taken in good part; for it means well, and may give ſome help to the underſtanding of what follows.</p>
            <p>When our Lord Jeſus was to leave the world, and to ſend his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours forth into the world, in his Name and ſtead, he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to <hi>preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> Mark 16.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Predicate Evangelium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word which our Lord Jeſus uſeth in this Commiſſion, is a word of Power and Authority; it comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>praeco;</hi> ſignifying an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171394:16"/>
Herauld, or Cryer: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to publiſh as an Herauld, to deliver in open place, in the hearing of a multitude, that many may take notice of it. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.27, <hi>Preach ye upon the houſe tops.</hi> Luke 12.3, <hi>That which ye have ſpoken in the ear, and in cloſets, ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed upon the houſe tops.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.7, <hi>Whereunto I am or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Preacher and an Apoſtle;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Cryer, an Herauld or Proclaimer, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Maximâ cum majeſtate ſummâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiâ, &amp; animi libertate, clariſſimè ac apertiſſimè denunciare.</hi> 2 Tim. 4.2, <hi>Preach the Word.</hi> Rom. 16.25. <hi>According to my Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the preaching of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1 Cor. 1.21, 23, Gal. 2.2. <hi>I communicated to them that Goſpel which I preach among the Gentiles; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quod praedico in Gentibus.</hi> Rom. 10.8, <hi>That is the word of faith which we preach.</hi> Rom. 10.15, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Quomodo verò praedicabunt, niſi mittantur? How ſhall they preach, except they be ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many might be the Scriptures which might be brought, to prove that the firſt Meſſengers were as ſo many Ambaſſadours, Heraulds, Proclaimers, Cryers, who with Majeſtie and Authority were ſent out to preach the Goſpel, as being deſigned of God, and ſet apart and commiſſioned by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt thereunto: and theſe are ſaid, <hi>eminentèr,</hi> to preach. When they publiſhed the Goſpel, they did it <hi>cum authoritate,</hi> by vertue of their Office, Calling, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation thereunto.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, (ſo abundantly overflowing was the grace of God, that) the beholders of it were ſo filled with joy and admiration, that where-ever they came, they could not chuſe but be telling what things they had heard and ſeen, and what had been done of them. Which notification of theirs, had many times this bleſſed effect, that it made the perſons to whom this ſtrangue (though good) news came, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to believe it, or to be enquirers after it, or deſirers of it: like that of old; <hi>O thou faireſt among women, whither is thy Beloved gone, that we may ſeek him with thee?</hi> Cant. 5.9. and 6.1. or that of the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Joh. 4.29, <hi>Come, ſee a man that told me all things whatever I did. Is not this the Chriſt?</hi> Joh. 4.39, 40, 41, 42, <hi>And many of the Samaritans believed on him, for the ſaying of the woman which teſtified; He told me all that ever I did. And many more believed, becauſe of his own word.</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171394:17"/>
ſuch was that of <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> who being ſo filled with the good news of her Lord's Reſurrection, that ſhe ran and told the Diſciples.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Luke</hi> 1.19. and 2.10, when the word <hi>Evangello</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Angel, it is rendered to ſhew or declare good news. But in <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18, when it's applied to Chriſt, it's rendered to preach the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Acts</hi> 21.26, <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to enter into the Temple, to <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> or <hi>declare</hi> the accompliſhment of the days of Purification: the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>annuntio.</hi> Which word is rendered, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.60, <hi>But go thou and preach the kingdom of God:</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntia regnum Dei: of <hi>Diangéllo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Luke</hi> 8.1, it's ſaid of Chriſt, He went <hi>preaching</hi> and evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelizing, or ſhewing the glad tidings of the Kingdom. And in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6, <hi>But when Timotheus came from you unto us, and</hi> brought us good tidings <hi>of your faith and charity,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7, <hi>As he hath declared to his ſervants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>To apply what hath been ſaid, to the Scriptures propounded touching the preaching of the ſcattered Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and <hi>Acts</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are not ſaid to <hi>preach, viz.</hi> to Proclaim, to Cry, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſignification of that word which was uſed by Chriſt when firſt he gave the Commiſſion, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is not ſaid (as here, Chriſt commanded) that they Preached the Goſpel; but, that they Evangelized; <hi>Evangelizantes verbum.</hi> Which word, though it be frequently tranſlated <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> which it may well bear when it is applied to ſuch as had power, that is, authority to preach the Evangel; yet it is diſtinguiſhed as a thing differing from preaching, when Evangelizing and Preaching come together. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.1, it's ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>He went thorow every city and village, Praedicans &amp; Evangelizans regnum Dei.</hi> They do not ſay in the Engliſh, <hi>Preaching and preaching the kingdom of God;</hi> but, <hi>Preaching and ſhewing the glad tidings of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> Which later expreſſion, ſhews the true proper mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Evangelizing,</hi> ſhewing or declaring glad tidings, whether by Preaching or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:171394:17"/>Of <hi>Philip</hi> it's ſaid, not onely that he <hi>evangelized,</hi> but it's alſo ſaid of him, that he <hi>preached Chriſt</hi> to them of <hi>Samaria;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.5. and he baptized them alſo, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12; which is not ſaid of any of the other Diſciples which were of this diſperſion, either in the eighth or eleventh Chapter.</p>
            <p>And not without ſome reaſon may this diſtinction be between <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> and the reſt of the diſperſion, foraſmuch as he was one of thoſe who was admitted into the ſervice of the Church by laying on of hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5, 6. and was alſo an Evangeliſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.8. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently one of thoſe the Apoſtle numbers up, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, which Chriſt gave <hi>for the work of the Miniſtery.</hi> Wherefore, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon may it be obſerved, that of him onely it is ſaid, He <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and baptized;</hi> of the reſt onely, They <hi>evangelized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Diſciples in <hi>Acts</hi> 11.19, 20, 'tis ſaid, They <hi>ſpake the word to none but to the Jews onely; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nemini loquentes verbum.</hi> So verſ. 20, <hi>Loquebantur ad Graecos, They ſpake unto the Graecians.</hi> The ſame word is uſed in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25, <hi>Loquimini quiſque veritatem proximo ſuo: Speak every man truth with his neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Where they are ſaid, in the next words, to <hi>evangelize the Lord Jeſus,</hi> which is tranſlated <hi>preach,</hi> both here, and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elſewhere; it is a word which ſignifieth to publiſh or declare good, being compounded of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bene,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Annuntiatio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> Joh. 20.18, ſhe did <hi>declare</hi> (or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to the Diſciples. So it is recorded of her, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.10, <hi>Illa profecto annunciavit iis qui cum ipſo fuerant:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: She did <hi>ſhew,</hi> or <hi>declare,</hi> or <hi>tell them that had been with him,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 28.10, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Annuntiate fratribus meis: Shew my brethren,</hi> or, declare to my brethren, <hi>that they go into Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would not conclude from theſe Scriptures, that <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> was a true Preacher of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and did truely evangelize the tidings thereof? Yet the Tranſlations render it, that ſhe <hi>told the diſciſples;</hi> and, <hi>Go, tell my diſciples:</hi> whenas, if it be well conſidered, it might as truely have been ſaid of <hi>Mary,</hi> that ſhe <hi>preached</hi> the Lord Jeſus and the Reſurrection, as it is ſaid of thoſe Diſciples in <hi>Acts</hi> 11.19, of whom it may be thus ſaid: That having by the providence of God been ſcattered, by means of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171394:18"/>
               <hi>Stephen</hi>'s perſecution, they could not but ſpeak the things which they had heard and ſeen, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.20. And in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2, 3, the two words are expreſſed which the Apoſtles uſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19, 20, touching theſe Diſciples: <hi>We cannot but ſpeak, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſhew unto you,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, it's rendered in Engliſh, <hi>We declare unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it might fall out with theſe Diſciples in their diſperſion, that the glory which they had ſeen, they could not but tell it, and declare it, and ſpeak it everywhere, as they went: and whereſoever the tidings of it came, it was news, and, in reſpect of the Subject of it, it was good news; it was <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or glad tidings.</p>
            <p>But as the tidings hereof was ſtrange and rare to the Gentiles, to whom it thus unexpectedly came: ſo the tidings of their receiving it by this means, and upon this occaſion, was as ſtrange to the Church at Jeruſalem; who, upon the hearing of it, ſent <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to Samaria, and <hi>Barnabas</hi> to Antioch. Which ſeems to me a thing needleſs, if, in the Church's account, the Diſciples Miniſtery had been eſteemed ſufficient for this work.</p>
            <p>But leſt it ſhould be thought this diſtinction may not be ſufficiently grounded upon the Word of Truth, but may ſavour of a Critical Curioſity; I ſhall ſubmit what hath been ſpoken, to the examination and cenſure of an Impartial Judgement.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, while that which hath been ſpoken lies under Examination, that which remains to be ſpoken, may ſerve to anſwer the Objection.</p>
            <p>Therefore I propoſe in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it might be ſuppoſed or admitted, that the ſcattered Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mentioned in the eighth and eleventh of the <hi>Acts,</hi> did as truely preach, as they were truely ſcattered; yet it's not ſaid that they did Baptize, as the Brethren do who urge this Scripture for their practice; <hi>Philip</hi> onely excepted, who is alſo called an Evangeliſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. which is a part of the gift given by Chriſt, for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12.</p>
            <p>Admit they did both Preach and Baptize, yet it muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that they were Diſciples who themſelves were Baptized: For they were members of the true Church at Hieruſalem, and ſcattered from thence, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1, 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171394:18"/>If the Brethren urging theſe for a pattern of Imitation for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Baptizing, will be meaſured by this pattern,</p>
            <p>It muſt be then ſuppoſed,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they be members of a truly-conſtituted viſible Church, as theſe of the Diſperſion were, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That they are gifted with the knowledge of Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of worſhip, and with thoſe gifts of the Holy Spirit, (now called extraordinary gifts) with which that Church was endued, and theſe ſcattered members amongſt others might not want their ſhare, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.3, 4, it's ſaid, <hi>that there appeared cloven tongues, like as of fire, and ſate upon each of them. And they were all filled with the holy Spirit, and began to ſpeak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt it ſhould be ſaid, This was onely the pouring out of the holy Spirit upon the Apoſtles, according to the promiſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4, 8; or if it do extend it ſelf to all preſent, it could be but to the hundred and twenty who continued together with one accord, waiting for the promiſe of the Father: And whereas there was a great and plentiful increaſe and addition of Believers and Diſciples to this firſt number, as appears, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41.47; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's ſaid, after this great increaſe and plentiful addition of Diſciples, in the fourth Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had been examined and threatned by the high-Prieſt and his accomplices, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.6, it's ſaid in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23, <hi>They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their owne company, and reported all that the chiefe Prieſts and Elders had ſaid of them. And when they heard that, they lift up their voyce with one accord, and ſaid, Lord, thou art the God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Company</hi> lift up their voyce, as well as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John:</hi> for it was done by them all with one accord. And in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30, 31, <hi>when they had prayed, the place was ſhaken where they were aſſembled together, and they were all filled with the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſpake the word of God with boldneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, That they go forth with a power and preſence of Jeſus Chriſt to the World, as Chriſt had promiſed to afford to thoſe firſt Meſſengers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20, <hi>Lo, I am with you;</hi> and accordingly did accompany their Meſſage for it's confirmation, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.20, <hi>The Lord working with them, confirming the Word with Signes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171394:19"/>
Which he alſo did manifeſt to <hi>Philip, Act.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7, who confirmed his word by the miracles which he did: which is not ſaid of the reſt of the Diſperſion who Evangelized, or (as we read it) Preached the Word. To all which this may againe be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,</p>
            <p>That no perſon did ever go forth, and Preach to the World the Goſpel of Chriſt ſincerely, in the Term that here is uſed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but was enabled to confirm that Word by the viſible preſence of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>viz.</hi> by Signes and Miracles: according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. to the end.</p>
            <p>And on the contrary, I read not that any which did Evangelize the Lord Jeſus to the World, either upon occaſion of their diſperſion, or otherwiſe, were ſo enabled to confirm their Doctrine; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles onely excepted, who did Preach as well as Evangelize; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did indeed preach the Evangel: according to that which is ſpoken of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.1. And theſe, as they did preach by Command and Authority: ſo they were enabled to confirm that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, by a viſible preſence of Chriſt with them. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Brethren therefore who urge theſe Scriptures for their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for Preaching and Baptizing one another, being meaſured by this pattern, I conceive their diſparity will be apparent, if it be but friendly and candidly conſidered; and may ſomewhat abate the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure which ſeems to be taken againſt thoſe who cannot practiſe as they do, for the Reaſons before alleadged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <hi>Object. Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf, that Chriſt ſent him not to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, but to Preach the Goſpel; Intimating, that to Baptize, is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to preaching: Therefore they which may do the greater, may do the leſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did Baptize as well as Preach, is evident from the ſame Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. where he ſaith, <hi>he baptized Criſpus and Gaius, and the houſhold of Stephanus:</hi> (and this he did not without Authority) the ſpeech therefore of the Apoſtle in ſaying, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to Baptize, but to Preach,</hi> is rather to be taken Comparatively, then Poſitively; not ſo much to Baptize, as to Preach: according to that ſaying in <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27, <hi>Labour not for the me at that periſheth, but for the meat which endureth unto everlasting life.</hi> Which expreſſion if it were Poſitive, that men were not to labour for the meat which periſheth, how ſhould that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171394:19"/>
be underſtood of the Apoſtle, which exhorts to labour? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 28. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10, <hi>This we commanded you that if any man would not work, he ſhould not eat.</hi> Beſides the example of himſelf, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.34, 35. Nor may it be therefore urged, that becauſe the Apoſtle uſeth this ſpeech comparatively, that therefore Baptiſme muſt be an Ordinance or Appointment of the Lord Jeſus inferiour to Preaching: for it would be inquired, Where this diſtinction of Superiority and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority, hath it's riſe and foundation among the Inſtitutions of Chriſt; and particularly between theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi> Preaching and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing: the rather, conſidering, that to whom, and at what time he gave the command touching Preaching; to them, and at that time, he gave the other touching Baptizing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. From whence this Concluſion hath been drawn (formerly, and as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to truth) That they which have power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Preach, have likewiſe power and authority to Baptize: Not from this Reaſon, becauſe that having power to do the greater, <hi>viz.</hi> Preaching; therefore they have power to do the leſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing: for this is a diſtinction made by ſome men, but not counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by the holy Scripture: But rather, in aſmuch as the Lord Jeſus did at one and the ſame time, to one and the ſelf-ſame perſons, give command that they ſhould both preach and baptize, and that by vertue of the power given to him; thence it follows moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that to them to whom power was given to Preach, to them alſo was authority given to Baptize: elſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had wanted authority for the baptizing of them he did baptize, or that he had no other then this, <hi>viz.</hi> that becauſe he might do the greater, which was to preach, therefore he might do the leſs, which was to Baptize. Which Concluſion, as it is not clear, ſo it is not ſafe, becauſe it is not found in Scripture. To which may be added theſe few words, which offer themſelves rather for a friendly trial, then for a poſitive aſſertion:</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth of himſelf, that he was <hi>one of the leaſt of the Apoſtles,</hi> and was as <hi>one born out of due time,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8, 9.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be obſerved, that to the Eleven was the command given to baptize the Nations, in expreſs termes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>We do not read that the ſame command was in ſo many words laid upon him, when he was called and ſent forth by the Lord Jeſus. In that he did baprize any one, it was not of his own head; for he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171394:20"/>
had <hi>the minde of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.16; who gave to his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours or Meſſengers not onely power to <hi>preach,</hi> but authority to <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptize</hi> alſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. And in that he was not more frequent in baptizing, or baptized no more, he was not thereunto ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſent as the former, who had the command in expreſs words. He had it onely in Authority, and therefore upon occaſion did exerciſe and perform it: They had it not onely in Authority, but alſo in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; therefore they muſt perform it, and might not omit it, they being ſent in an eſpecial manner thereunto.</p>
            <p>This kinde of reaſoning the Apoſtle gives occaſion for in another caſe, touching the exerciſe of his Miniſtery; whereas he teſtifieth of himſelf, in a eſpecial manner that he was an <hi>Apoſtle of the Gentiles,</hi> and therein did <hi>magnifie</hi> his <hi>office,</hi> Rom. 11.13; and that unto <hi>Peter</hi> was committed the <hi>Apoſtleſhip of the Circumciſion,</hi> Gal. 2. 7, 8, 9, as unto him the <hi>Goſpel of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion.</hi> And this diſtribution was very eminent; yet not ſo, but that <hi>Peter</hi> might preach to the Gentiles, as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo did to the Jews, as appeareth by his frequent preaching in the Synagogues, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whence may be concluded, Though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Miſſion to the Gentiles, whoſe Ambaſſadour or Apoſtle he particularly was; yet he alſo might preach to the Jews, where-ever they were, and that without ſin; which accordingly he did, (as many places teſtifie.) So, although the ſame Apoſtle, when he was at firſt called, had not an expreſs Command touching Baptiſm, as the Eleven had, (in ſo many words;) yet nevertheleſs he wanted not ſufficient Authority for to baptize thoſe whom he did baptize, without degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Ordinance, and making of it inferiour to Preaching, as this Objection would infer from the Apoſtle's ſpeech, when he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to evangelize.</hi> Which inference being inforced as a conſequence, needs a proof from Scripture, before it can impoſe belief upon any perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <hi>Object.</hi> When Chriſt gave power and authority to the eleven Diſciples to <hi>teach all nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, Son and holy Spirit,</hi> he added, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20, <hi>Lo, I am with you all the days, even unto the end of the world.</hi> How is this Scripture fulfilled, if there be not a Miniſtery continued to the end of the world?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This command of Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and this promiſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171394:20"/>
of his preſence with them to the end of the world, muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as being made to thoſe eleven individual perſons, or elſe with ſuch others as were to ſucceed them in that work of Miniſtery, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, Son and holy Spirit, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever Chriſt had commanded them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If it reſpecteth the Eleven onely, then there muſt be another underſtanding of thoſe words, <hi>The end of the world,</hi> then is moſt commonly received: for, according to the common acceptation of <hi>the end of the world,</hi> taking it for the utmoſt and extremeſt part of time, ſo it could not be applied to the Apoſtles perſonally; who lived not to ſee the end of the world in that ſence; according to that Scripture, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.5, <hi>Your fathers, where are they? the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, do they live forever?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If it reſpect a Succeſſion of Miniſtery, it muſt be either an Apoſtolical National Miniſtery, for breeding the Church; or a Paſtoral Congregational Miniſtery for feeding the Church; or both.</p>
            <p>Now that this Succeſſion of Miniſtery, in both or either of theſe kindes, is not ſo viſible (as it's commonly judged) hath been already proved, and needs not again be repeated.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it hence follow, that any imputation of unfaithfulneſs ſhould be fixed upon the moſt righteous God; as if he muſt needs be rendered unrighteous, unleſs there be a continuation of Miniſtery, either Apoſtolical or Paſtoral, becauſe that he hath ſaid, that they, teaching the Nations to obſerve whatſoever he had commanded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> lo, he was with them <hi>all the days, to the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this may the more clearly appear, conſider what is ſpoken touching <hi>Eli</hi> and his houſe, in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30, to the end. <hi>I ſaid that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father, ſhould walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me for ever; i. e.</hi> in the Prieſthood, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1, 41, 43. <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.13, 14, 15. <hi>But now the Lord ſaith, Be it far from me: for them that honour me, I will honour; and they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God had promiſed <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſeed after him, and that by a Statute for ever, the execution of the Prieſts office, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.15: yet there was implied in this promiſe this condition, that they ſhould continue to honour God in that Adminiſtration. And though this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171394:21"/>
was not expreſt, it was ever underſtood, as is evident, <hi>de facto,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> Levit. 10. who, for offering with ſtrange fire which the Lord commanded them not, were devoured by fire from the Lord.<note place="margin">Levit. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>And Moſes ſaid, This is that the Lord ſaid, I will be ſanctified in all them that come nigh me, and before all the people will I be glorified. And Aaron held his peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like manner of God's proceedings doth appear, in expreſs terms, in the caſe of <hi>Eli</hi> and his ſons, in the place before alleadged; though God had ſaid, touching him and his father's houſe, that they ſhould walk before him for ever, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. and yet doth there ſay, <hi>Behold I will cut off thine arm, and the arm of thy fathers houſe. And the man of thine which I ſhall not cut off from my altar, ſhall be to conſume thine eyes, and to grieve thy heart. And he that is left in thy houſe, ſhall ſay, Put me, I pray thee, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of the Prieſts offices that I may eat a piece of bread.</hi> Which was accordingly fulfilled in the next Chapter, and in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.27.</p>
            <p>The Lord gives the reaſon of this ſeeming-contradiction, why he ſhould ſay of <hi>Eli,</hi> and of his father's houſe, that they ſhould walk before him in the Prieſthood for ever; and yet doth alſo declare and accordingly accompliſh, that the Continuation or Succeſſion ſhall be cut off; as it was from the poſterity of <hi>Eli,</hi> and likewiſe from the line of <hi>Aaron,</hi> before the time of the expiration of the Moſaical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. The reaſon of this the Lord expreſſeth, in theſe words: <hi>But now be it far from me: for, them that honour me, I will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though, with reſpect to the Eternal condition of believers, <hi>the foundation of God ſtands ſure, having this ſeal, The Lord knows who are his,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19. and that <hi>there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8.1. and though <hi>neither life, nor death, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate</hi> a believer <hi>from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8. <hi>ult.</hi> foraſmuch as the <hi>Father which gave them</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>is greater then all, and none ſhall be able to pluck them out of the Fathers hands,</hi> Joh. 10.28, 29. nay, <hi>ſin</hi> it ſelf <hi>ſhall not</hi> be able to <hi>have dominion over</hi> them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25, 26. Yet, with reſpect to any External condition which may befal them, how eminently-glorious ſoever it may be, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171394:21"/>
what promiſe ſoever may be made unto it, yet the Equity of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is implied, if not expreſſed, that the perſon to whom ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of External bleſſing or preſence is made, are engaged to walk with God, to be found honouring of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this is the Entail to be reckoned; and God no longer can in faith be expected to perform his part, then ſuch a perſon or people are found faithful with God on their part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that honours me, I will honour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30, 31, &amp;c. 1 Chron. 28.7, 9, <hi>If thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever.</hi> Which <hi>forſaking</hi> and <hi>caſting off,</hi> are expounded in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30, 31, 32, 33, 34: <hi>If his children forſake my law, and walk not in my judgements, I will viſit their tranſgreſſions with the rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes: nevertheleſs my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from him, nor ſuffer my faithfulneſs to fail.</hi> And in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, may be ſeen at large the Covenant God made with <hi>Solomon</hi> touching the Temple and its continuance. <hi>For now have I choſen and ſanctified this houſe, that my Name may be there for ever: and my eyes and my heart ſhall be there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually. And as for thee, if thou wilt walk before me as David thy father walked, and do according to all I command thee; then I will eſtabliſh the throne of thy kingdom, according as I have co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted with David thy father. But if ye turn away and forſake my ſtatutes and my commandments which I have ſet before you, and go and ſerve other gods, and worſhip them; then I will pluck them up by the roots, and this houſe will I caſt out of my ſight, and make it to be a Proverb, and a by-word among all nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame thing is declared by the Lord to <hi>Aſa,</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2, <hi>Hear ye me, Aſa, and all Judah and Benjamin; the Lord is with you, while ye be with him: if ye ſeek him he will be found of you; but if you for ſake him, he will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which thing the Lord did accompliſh to a tittle, as to their exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal enjoyments, both as concerning their Land, their Temple, and all their outward glory.</p>
            <p>Now from the preceding paſſages of the Scripture, it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the Lord, when he made any promiſe of an external concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or conſideration, it did alwayes import that man was bound as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171394:22"/>
well on his part, to a holy, and faithful, and obedient walking with God, as he was to expect a faithful performance on Gods part, of the thing promiſed; and that a neglect on mans part did neceſſarily infer a diſobligement on Gods part. <hi>The Lord is with you while you are with him: but if you forſake him he will forſake you,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.2. Or as to <hi>Eli, He that honoureth me, I will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; but he that diſpiſeth me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. Nor doth it ſeem to have been his minde of Old onely, as under that diſpenſation; but in the very place mentioned, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> the laſt, beſides the equity of the thing, that very Scripture holds forth no leſs then what hath been already propounded. For there, as he promiſeth <hi>to be with them all the dayes, to the end of the world;</hi> ſo he commanded <hi>that they ſhould continue teaching the nations to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them.</hi> For he ſaith not, <hi>Teach the nations to obſerve all things,</hi> but <hi>teaching;</hi> which being a Participle of the preſent tenſe, ſignifieth the doing, and continuance in doing the thing which is commanded, and whereunto the promiſe of his preſence is annexed. So that if Chriſt did promiſe his preſence with a Miniſtery to the end of the world, it was with them, <hi>teaching the nations to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them</hi> or with ſuch a Miniſtery as did <hi>teach and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the nations,</hi> and continue <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them.</hi> But if that Miniſtery, in ſtead of <hi>teaching the nations whatſoever Chriſt commanded,</hi> ſhould either ceaſe <hi>to teach the nations</hi> at all, or teach them that which Chriſt commanded them not; or ſhould teach them to obſerve the precepts of men, in ſtead of the commandments of Chriſt; the continuance of the preſence of Chriſt with ſuch a Miniſtery is not to be concluded upon, as if it were entailed upon it by this Scripture: But rather that equity of God held forth in the former Scriptures, is to take place here: <hi>Him that honoureth me, I will honour: but he that diſpiſeth me, ſhall be lightly eſteeemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is not onely true with reſpect to the Nations Miniſtery, or the Miniſtery appointed by Chriſt <hi>to teach and baptize the nations;</hi> but alſo touching the Miniſtery in the Churches: That if they alſo continue not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, or ſhall not continue <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to obſerve all things, what Chriſt hath commanded them,</hi> His preſence is not obliged to to be with them neither, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171394:22"/>
compared with the fifth: the truth of this to be extended both to Church and Miniſtery, as of old to the Prieſthood and the Temple; and no unrighteouſneſs to be fixed upon God, neither then nor now, for ſuffering them to be eclipſed or diſcontinued. Foraſmuch as they ceaſed to honour God, no wonder if God ceaſe to honour them with his preſence: and when they began to diſpiſe him he alſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed of them. And this hath been the condition of the Chriſtian Churches and Miniſtery; and ſo it's like to be, until the day of the Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>It's alſo to be remembred, that a people, by their miſuſing of a mercy or bleſſing, may draw upon themſelves a diſcontinuance of that bleſſiing or mercy for a ſeaſon; which may not extend ſo far as to an annihilation or extirpation thereof, but that it may have its poſſibility of reſtauration, and in due time its real accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>It's ſaid, touching the Land of <hi>Canaan, Gen.</hi> 17.8, <hi>I will give to thee and thy ſeed after thee, the land of thy ſojourning, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting poſſeſſion,</hi> Gen. 48.4.</p>
            <p>Yet it is not unknown how this promiſe, which ſeemes to be made to them abſolutely, hath by their ſinnings and tranſgreſſions againſt God, at all times not been performed; but that people have been ſpewed out, even by their own Land; according as it was intimated to them by <hi>Moſes, Levit.</hi> 18.28, <hi>That the land ſpew not you out alſo when you defile it, as it ſpewed out the nations that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you,</hi> Levit. 20.22. Which thing he alſo accompliſhed according to his word by <hi>Ieremiah, Chap.</hi> 7.15, 16, 19, and many other places: which had its particular fulfilling; in their ſeveral Captivities under <hi>Hoſhea, Salmaneſer,</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah.</hi> But though they were depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their poſſeſſions for a time, yet not of their right of inheritance; that was theirs ſtill; and accordingly, after their land had fulfilled her Sabbaths, and they had continued in their baniſhed condition accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their time appointed, ſeventy years; they were returned into their own land (as it is called) according to the Word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>So was it touching their Temple-ſtate; God had ſaid, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.3, <hi>I have hallowed this houſe which thou haſt built, to put my Name there for ever: and mine eyes and my heart ſhall be there perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.16.</p>
            <p>Now as the extent or duration of this Temple, and its worſhip, was to expire in the fulneſs of time, as all other legal Miniſtrations were,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171394:23"/>
in the appearing of the Lord Jeſus, and the ſubſtituting of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church and Miniſtery; yet before this time was fully come wherein the Veil of the Temple was to be rent, and <hi>Moſes</hi> to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, as to his Adminiſtration; I ſay, Before this time was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, this Temple and its Worſhip fell under a Diſcontinuance and Diſuſe, by reaſon of the ſins of the Prieſts and People; according as the Lord had ſaid, in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.19, 20, 21, 22, and had according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effected in proceſs of time, as appears in the Captivity by <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> and in the <hi>Lamentations,</hi> Chap. 2.6, 7. <hi>He hath violently taken away his tabernacle as a garden; he hath deſtroyed his palaces of the aſſembly: the Lord hath cauſed the ſolemn feaſts and ſabbaths to be forgotten in Sion, and deſpiſed in the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his anger the king and the prieſts: the Lord hath caſt off his altar, he hath abhorred his ſanctuary, he hath given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces: they have made a noiſe in the houſe of the Lord, as in the day of a ſolemn feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding which dealing of his towards them, he cauſed them to return at the time appointed, to build their walls, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore their Worſhip, according to the Word which he had ſpoken by his holy Prophets, becauſe as yet the full time was not come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Entail was to be cut off from this people.</p>
            <p>That which I would have obſerved in this Circumlocution, is this: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That although God had promiſed that his eyes and his heart ſhould be upon that houſe which <hi>Solomon</hi> had built, perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yet that time was a prefixt and limited time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That before the time limited wherein there was to be a ceſſation of the Temple and Temple-Worſhip, there was a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance, as to the enjoyment and exerciſe of it, which befel that people through their tranſgreſſions and ſin; inſomuch that it may be ſaid, They ſinned themſelves into a difuſe of their Mercy; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel them for a time, during their Captivity, till their reſtoration.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That whereas it was by divine intendment, that at the time appointed the daily ſacrifice ſhould ceaſe, the Temple-work and Worſhip ſhould be at an end, of which expiration God himſelf would be the author and procurer; yet theſe people beforehand, by their ſins, procured themſelves a Separation, Baniſhment, and Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171394:23"/>
for the ſpace of ſeventy yeers; though then, at the end thereof, God graciouſly returned their Captivity.</p>
            <p>So would I that it were conſidered touching the promiſe of our Lord Jeſus to the Apoſtles, or to the Chriſtian Miniſtery, <hi>Lo, I am with you all the days unto the end of the world:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That there is a time limited for the continuation of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them as a Miniſtery, at which time there is to be a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, as to a Miniſtery, when the work for which the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery was given, is fulfilled, according to <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12.13, 14. and this according to divine purpoſe, and fore-appointment of God, <hi>Till we all come to the unity of the faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That it's poſſible for the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, in the work of their Miniſtery, to make <hi>ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience,</hi> to prove falſe Teachers, and <hi>privily</hi> to <hi>bring in damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrines,</hi> and <hi>through covetouſneſs to make merchandice of</hi> men; proving ſpots and blemiſhes, ſporting themſelves with their own deceivings; <hi>having eyes full of adultery, that cannot ceaſe from ſin;</hi> beguiling unſtable ſouls, exerciſed with covetous practices; <hi>curſed children,</hi> which have forſaken the right way, and gone aſtray, <hi>following the way of Balaam the ſon of Boſor, who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, all this the holy Apoſtles of our Lord did foretel ſhould be, as may particularly be inſtanced in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul Peter, Jude;</hi> and this iniquity began to work in a Myſtery before the Apoſtles left the earth, and afterwards mightily prevailed, as the Hiſtory of time will evidence; and moſt eminently, that learned Diſcourſe of Maſter <hi>Mede,</hi> called <hi>The Apoſtacie of the laſt times,</hi> and <hi>Clappam</hi>'s Brief upon the Bible; and became as that Scripture ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.8, <hi>The prieſts and the prophets erred through ſtrong drink; they are ſwallowed up of wine; they are out of the way through ſtrong drink. They erre in viſion, they ſtumble in judgement: for all tables are full of vomit and filthineſs; there is no place clean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this will be found to have been the condition of the Miniſtery ſoon after the Apoſtles time, and ſo forward ever ſince that pretended Vicar of Chriſt that falſe Vice-Chriſt, hath, <hi>as God,</hi> ſet himſelf <hi>in the temple of God,</hi> and hath ſent forth his Angels, Meſſengers, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>viz.</hi> Nuntio's Cardinals Legats, and what not? whereby he hath darkened the counſel of God, by feigned and deviſed words and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:171394:24"/>From which we may expect to be delivered, when the moſt High ſhall ſend his great Angel to enlighten the earth with his glory. The fields being now grown almoſt <hi>white to the harveſt,</hi> the <hi>Lord of the harveſt</hi> will, in mercy to the ignorance of his poor people, <hi>thruſt forth labourers into the harveſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh turn again our Captivity</hi> (alſo) <hi>as the rivers of the ſouth,</hi> who are fallen under a diſuſe of our mercy, our firſt Miniſtery, which our Lord, aſcending on high, <hi>gave,</hi> as <hi>gifts to men, for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the number <hi>of the Saints,</hi> and <hi>edifying the body of Chriſt:</hi> which though diſcontinued, becauſe of our and our forefathers ſins, yet may be reſtored to us again, when we are brought to ſee a want of them, and can cry unto God for them. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.18, 19, 20, <hi>The Lord is a God of judgement: bleſſed are all they that wait for him. And though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, and the water of affliction, yet ſhall not thy teachers be removed into a corner any more: but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>whom ſhall he teach knowledge, and whom ſhall he cauſe to underſtand doctrine? Them that are weaned from the milk, and drawn from the breſts,</hi> Iſa. 28.9.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as in the former times there hath been a diſcontinuance of the true Miniſtery for a long ſeaſon, by reaſon of tranſgreſſion; yet may there be a glorious reſtoration thereof alſo, in God's due time. For as the Apoſtacie began at the Miniſtery, both in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and later times; as is witneſſed by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, <hi>There were falſe prophets among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who ſhall privily bring in damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift damnation.</hi> And yet from the former, the Lord in his good pleaſure ſet his people of old free. For theſe reaſons, why may it not alſo be hoped, that in due time he will again return in mercy, and viſit the dark corners of the earth, cauſing the people that <hi>ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death,</hi> to hear the joyful ſound, that they may walk in the light of his countenance?</p>
            <p>The rather, conſidering that the Miniſtery was given to continue till the number of the Saints were perfected, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. or, as the former Tranſlation renders it, <hi>For the gathering together of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the number of the Saints be not perfected, nor their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171394:24"/>
together compleated, How is the end for which Chriſt aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for which he gave gifts to men, accompliſhed, if <hi>the work of the Miniſtery</hi> be not again reſtored unto its priſtine and primitive Conſtitution? as well to reſpect the Nations which are <hi>without,</hi> viz. <hi>the out-caſts of Iſrael,</hi> together with thoſe worſhippers of the Sun and Moon, the Moors and Indians, and the people that know not God, nor have ever heard the ſound of him, nor of the ſalvation which through Chriſt Jeſus he holds forth to Mankinde; as well as that ſort of Miniſtery which it's ſuppoſed is found among good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who judge they are in Church-eſtate already, though indeed they are both but the fruit of the ſame aſcenſion; and both reſpect the ſame end, Miniſtery, and duration or continuance: For as the Saints (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuch) are not come to a perfect man in Chriſt, and therefore have need of an edifying feeding Miniſtery; ſo the number of them which are to be gathered, are likewiſe not compleated, and therefore need a gathering and breeding Miniſtery: the one, without the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not perfect; eſpecially, the later not without the former.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as the Miniſtery for the World, as it was firſt given, namely, to the Apoſtles, in theſe words; <hi>Go ye into all the world,</hi> or <hi>Teach all nations:</hi> ſo it was comprehenſive, and took in the later, and ſtood ſometimes without it, they holding out the breſt of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and confirmation to thoſe to whom they had been (as a womb) parental or inſtrumental in converſion. Therefore, in a return of mercy, as in point of Miniſtery, it would be conſidered, Whether the firſt Apoſtolical and National Miniſtery be not again to be looked for, hoped for, and longed for, and prayed for, and that by way of eminency; not onely for <hi>Sion</hi>'s ſake, and for <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s ſake, but alſo for the Nations ſakes, the Kindreds, Tongues, Peoples, thoſe who know not God; conſidering that there is a time wherein <hi>John,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaten the book, was to propheſie <hi>again, before many people, and nations, and tongues, and kings,</hi> Rev. 10. <hi>ult.</hi> And the Angel which he ſaw flying in the midſt of heaven, was to <hi>preach the ancient Goſpel to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people.</hi> And this was to follow Antichriſt's univerſal over-ſpreading of the earth: for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had prevailed ſo far, as to cauſe all, both ſmall and great, rich and poor, bond and free, to receive his mark; and that no man might buy or ſell but he that had received the mark; and that <hi>all the world wondered after the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.3, 16, 17. after this great
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171394:25"/>
power and prevalencie of Antichriſt then ſhould the <hi>ancient Goſpel be preached to every nation, kinred, tongue, and people, that dwell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth,</hi> Rev. 14.6. and then ſhould follow the fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> v 8; there followed <hi>another Angel ſaying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen;</hi> and this ſhould be that Angel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.1, 2, which ſhould <hi>come down from heaven with great power, and enlighten the earth with his glory,</hi> and ſhould <hi>cry mightily with a ſtrong voice, ſaying, Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon the great is fallen;</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8, <hi>Then ſhall that wicked be revealed, whom God ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and deſtroy with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whether this be not that Miniſtery which the Lord will ſend forth, to gather his choſen ones from the four corners of the windes, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. foraſmuch as after that the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall ſhew their ſeducing ſignes and wonders to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if it were poſſible, the very elect,</hi> verſ. 22. and that <hi>great tribulation</hi> ſhall happen; <hi>the ſun darkned, and the moon not give her light: Then ſhall the Son of man come in the clouds, with great power and glory, and ſhall ſend his Angels,</hi> or Meſſengers, <hi>and ſhall gather together his elect from the utmoſt parts of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which, it were to be deſired that the Lord would ſtir up the hearts of his people to cry mightily to him, and give him no reſt, till he accompliſh the work of gathering together his number out of all Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and Peoples; <hi>the utmoſt parts of the Heathen</hi> being given to Chriſt as his peculiar <hi>inheritance,</hi> Pſal. 2.8. and becauſe <hi>from the riſing of the ſun, to the going down of the ſame,</hi> God's <hi>name ſhall be great among the Gentiles,</hi> Mal. 1.11.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If this be true which hath been ſpoken, then we muſt expect more Apoſtles; but it is ſaid in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9, that thoſe were the <hi>laſt Apoſtles:</hi> Therefore there can be no ground to expect any more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That Scripture concludes not againſt what hath been ſpoken, as will appear, when it is examined.</p>
            <p>The word which is rendered there <hi>laſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is, in <hi>Luke</hi> 14.9, taken for the <hi>loweſt</hi> or <hi>meaneſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, When thou art bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of any man to a wedding, go ſit down in the</hi> loweſt room. And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171394:25"/>
this ſignification of the word, may very well agree with that which is the Argument of this Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9, and ſo it ſeems to be carried. <hi>I think God hath ſet forth us the Apoſtles laſt,</hi> (i. e. loweſt, or vileſt) <hi>as it were men appointed to death. For we are made a ſpectacle unto the world, to Angels, and men. We are fooles for Chriſts ſake, but ye are wiſe. We are made the filth of the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things to this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be conſidered whether all theſe ſeveral expreſſions do not more properly agree to the word, as it is rendered the <hi>loweſt</hi> or <hi>baſeſt,</hi> then to the word <hi>laſt Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If the word he to be taken for the <hi>laſt,</hi> yet it doth not neceſſarily inforce it ſelf to be underſtood of the laſt of what ſhall be, but the laſt of what hath been: therefore it is rendred <hi>noviſſimus,</hi> the neweſt, as our Engliſh Dialect will infer: the laſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or neweſt garment, are Synonimaes. In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, it's rendered not <hi>laſt,</hi> but <hi>later.</hi> And 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, ſpeaking of Chriſt, it's ſaid, <hi>He was made manifeſt in the laſt dayes.</hi> Heb. 1.2, it's ſaid, <hi>In theſe laſt dayes God hath ſpoken unto us by his Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>laſt dayes</hi> may not be ſo underſtood, as if they were ſo the laſt, that there were no more dayes to ſucceed them; for there hath been ſixteen hundred years of dayes ſince that time, paſt and gone: neither may I conceive thoſe Apoſtles were the laſt, or ſo the laſt Apoſtles, that there ſhould no more come after them; under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding them to be Meſſengers ſent forth, as the term Apoſtle imports: for then I would inquire, By whom ſhould <hi>the out caſts of Iſrael</hi> be gathered, or the Nations converted to the faith of Chriſt? <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.37, 38. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.14.</p>
            <p>If there be any Nations of the World, Kindreds, Tongues, and People, to whom the Goſpel hath not been ſent; it muſt be done to fulfill the Word of the Lord. And by whom ſhall it be done, but by ſuch Meſſengers which ſhall be endued with like power of Evidence and Demonſtration, both of Tongues and Gifts, as the firſt Meſſengers or Apoſtles had, to preach to the Nations in their proper Language? Therefore this Scripture, rightly underſtood, is not of force againſt what hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The Scriptures of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Object.</note> they may in a ſence be called the Apoſtles: And as the Apoſtle ſpake to the <hi>Corinthians,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171394:26"/>
If I be not an Apoſtle to others, yet I am one to you;</hi> ſo of their Writings, If they be not Apoſtles to others to whom they are not come, yet they are ſo to them to whom they are come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Their Writings may be called Apoſtles in a figure, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was a Prophet to the Eunuch, into whoſe hands his Prophecie came, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30; but as he needed one to guide him to underſtand that Prophet, ſo do we ſtand in need of a guide to underſtand the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in their writings.</p>
            <p>And that God who was pleaſed to ſend his Meſſenger to the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, to inſtruct him, and to cauſe him to underſtand what he read, may in his due time ſend out his Meſſengers againe, in the Power and Spirit of the former, to open to us not onely <hi>Moſes,</hi> but Chriſt and his Apoſtles; whoſe writings, we have but ſeen them as he who <hi>ſaw men walking like trees,</hi> or as the Eunuch did the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> before it was expounded.</p>
            <p>If it were but in the heart of Gods People to miſtruſt their own underſtanding, and but to ſee need to cry out to the Lord to reſtore the ancient Goſpel, and to ſend out thoſe Meſſengers which are to Preach to the World his fear and worſhip, according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6, 7, to diſcover <hi>Babylon,</hi> and mightily to call out his People from thence, and to lead to <hi>Sion;</hi> it would not be long before ſome great thing might be accompliſhed. But while we are apt to think we can do theſe things of our ſelves, without any farther help, no marvel that as yet deliverance comes not. Oh if the Lord of the harveſt muſt be ſought to finde labourers, and to thruſt them forth; and if he will be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of for this to do it; why do the Lords remembrancers keep ſilence, and give him any reſt, <hi>till he make Hieruſalem a praiſe in the earth, till he build up Sion, and gather her ſtones out of the rubbiſh of Babylons confuſions!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But whatever may be pretended for a neceſſity of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery to the World, yet <hi>Paul</hi> took care for the Ordinances and Miniſtery of the Churches, when he gave <hi>Timothy</hi> inſtructions how to behave himſelf in the Church of the living God; and gave him a command to commit that which he had taught him, to faithful men, who might be able to teach others alſo, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is moſt certaine he did ſo; and by this place and many others, appeares the plentiful proviſion the Lord made for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in point of Ordinances, ſo far as concerned the rules and laws of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171394:26"/>
Worſhip, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. from <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17, to the 32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2, and almoſt thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>But though he were faithful in appointing the rules for Worſhip, and giving Laws thereof, and committing the ſame to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and by him to faithful men, that they ſhould teach others alſo; yet how treacherous they would in after-times prove to thoſe Rules and Laws of Worſhip, is likewiſe Propheſied of, and foretold, which ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal the Chriſtian Churches, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29, 30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Jud.</hi> 17.18: and this Apoſtacy was actually begun in the Apoſtles dayes, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, and in the dayes of the firſt Churches, <hi>Rev. Chap.</hi> 2. and 3. which Apoſtacy was grown to be univerſal, in <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi> And how univerſal it was, they that will take pains to compare the Hiſtory of times, may finde, to their aſtoniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note> But ſuppoſe the Apoſtacy were every way ſuch as hath been ſpoken, May not the People of the Lord, who are the Saints of the moſt High, the Kings and Prieſts of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10, may not Believers now being Kings by Jeſus Chriſt, reſtore the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſet up the Ordinances of Chriſt, as well as <hi>Joſiah</hi> the King did, who ſet up and repaired what the former evill Kings had broken down and deſtroyed? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The building the Houſe,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and appointing the Laws and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Houſe of God, was by him committed, Firſt to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 39.32, 42, 43, who was Prince of the People, the firſt Kingly Magiſtrate and he who received from the Lord the pattern of his Houſe, and the Laws thereof; and he was a Type of Chriſt. Next to him, <hi>Joſhuah</hi> renewed the Covenant of the Lord with the People, at the Commandment of the Lord, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5. from the ſecond <hi>verſe</hi> to the ninth. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.25, 26, 27. This <hi>Joſhuah</hi> was a Type of Jeſus, and called by that name, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.45. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>When the Tabernacle ceaſed, and the Temple came in the roome of it, the Lord gave King <hi>David</hi> the pattern thereof; and he to <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. from <hi>verſe</hi> 11, to 21; and they were both Types of Chriſt, as Kings.</p>
            <p>Now as to the King it was given to build at firſt, and to appoint the Laws of the Houſe at firſt; ſo to the Kings was it appointed to repaire the breaches, when any were. The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171394:27"/>
Royal Prieſthood, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6, yet they might not meddle with the Prieſts Office, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.9, 10. They were a Kingly People, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed Nation, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.15; yet they did not all raign as Kings, nor did the People ſet about the reſtoring or repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what was amiſſe, till ſuch to whom it was by order appointed to be their head, did ſet upon the work. Neither in the Tabernacle without <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor in the Circumciſion of thoſe who were born in the wilderneſs, without <hi>Joſhua;</hi> nor in the Temple, without <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Solomon;</hi> nor in the repairing the Temple, without their Kings, as <hi>Joſiah, Hezekiah,</hi> &amp;c. nor in the coming out of Babylon, without <hi>Zerubbabel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Declaring plainly, that to them to whom at firſt was given the power of building the Houſe, and appointing the Laws thereof, to them did appertain the right of repairing the breach, and reſtoring the Laws; which were ſuch perſons as did type out the Lord Jeſus, who, as at firſt he became the <hi>corner-ſtone</hi> of the building, and did by his Meſſengers, his Apoſtles and Miniſters, with whom he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his viſible preſence, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 28, 19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. <hi>ult. Joh.</hi> 15. the laſt words of verſ. 5.) lay the foundation, and build the ſuperſtructure, according to <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12: ſo to the ſame Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by his Miniſtery, accompanied with his Power and Preſence, doth it of right belong to be the <hi>Repairer of the breaches</hi> which Antichriſt hath made in the Chriſtian Church, and the <hi>Reſtorer of paths to walk in;</hi> as of old was typed out in the Temple-ſtate, in the examples before alleadged.</p>
            <p>Once the Lord Jeſus taught the people by himſelf, from the days of his entering upon the work of the Miniſtery, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18, till the time of finiſhing of that Miniſtration. Afterward, he performed it by his Apoſtles, whom he had choſen, ordained, and ſent out for that purpoſe; together with thoſe other gifts of Miniſtery, which, as the fruit of his aſcenſion to his Father, he gave for that end, to <hi>perfect,</hi> i. e. to <hi>gather</hi> and <hi>edifie</hi> his Body the Church; until they ſhould <hi>all come in the unity of the faith,</hi> and of the knowledge of the Son of God, <hi>to a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He did not leave it upon his people promiſcuouſly, to be equally and alike gifted for that work. Compare <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29.</p>
            <p>Therefore there doth remain an Order to be obſerved in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171394:27"/>
of the Miniſtery; and the Diſorder thereof is to be bewailed; and Jeſus Chriſt, to whom all power is given of the Father, and by whom at firſt it was derived and delegated to choſen men, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.40, 41, 42, to be waited upon for reſtoration thereof; in whoſe hand the power is, and without whom, <hi>we can do nothing,</hi> Joh. 15.5.</p>
            <p>That he ſhould do it by ſuch inſtruments as he pleaſeth, furniſhed with ſuch power and authority, and with ſuch a preſence of Chriſt, as may demonſtrate them to be ſent of God for that work or ſervice, by the Divine light and heat of the fire of the Spirit of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. furniſhing them with the true knowledge of the mind of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Fundamentals of
<list>
                  <item>Doctrine,</item>
                  <item>Worſhip;</item>
               </list>
together with true power to evince the truth thereof againſt all gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, of whom the world was never more full; whether we reſpect
<list>
                  <item>Jews,</item>
                  <item>or Infidels,</item>
                  <item>or Falſe Chriſtians.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To be furniſhed with ability to ſhew to all Kindreds, Nations, Tongues, and Peoples, the glory of the Myſtery of the <hi>ancient Goſpel,</hi> which once was declared and received, but from which there hath been ſo deep a <hi>falling away;</hi> according as was foretold, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, and accordingly effected, through the power of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is not the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles as efficacious to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Saints of the enjoyment of their Liberties purchaſed by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> and to put them upon the doing their duties required of them, in our Times, as it was in theirs; ſeeing that they, by their Miniſtery, were commanded to <hi>teach all nations to obſerve whatſoever Chriſt had commanded them?</hi> Matth. 28.19, 20. Rom. 10.6, 7, 8. 2 Tim. 2.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Miniſtery of the Apoſtles may be conſidered,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> either in the <hi>word,</hi> or in the <hi>power</hi> of it, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. The <hi>word</hi> of their Miniſtery, without the <hi>power,</hi> is not efficacious to put perſons upon their duty, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.11, 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>The Power accompanying the Word, is either Outward or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or both Outward and Inward.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:171394:28"/>The Outward power, was the external demonſtration of the Spirit, expreſſed <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.18, 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>The Inward power, was that internal operation of the Spirit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14.</p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>word</hi> of the Apoſtles Miniſtery be accompanied with a <hi>power, and demonſtration of the Spirit,</hi> ſutable to that demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and power will be the manifeſtation of the obedience that follows it; according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>demonſtration</hi> of the Spirit be viſible and outward, it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to the Outward obedience, according to the Rules of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration. If it be accompanied with <hi>power,</hi> it not onely directs, but enables to obedience in that particular; according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>demonſtration</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the Spirit be onely Inward and Inviſible, it [directs] and [enables] to the more Inward and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible part of obedience, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23, to believe, hope, joy, love; and to expreſs the fruits thereof, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.26.</p>
            <p>If the demonſtration and power of the Spirit which accompanieth the Word, be both Outward and Inward; then doth it direct and enable the ſoul both Inwardly and Outwardly to be obedient, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>Now it may ſo come to paſs, that the Word of the Lord, or the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles, may come in demonſtration and power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the outward man onely, and extend no further: it may convince [that] <hi>Acts</hi> 4.14, 16, and may bring that under obedience, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12, 13. but it ſeldome or never befals the Lord's people, to be convinced in the outward man onely; (I ſay <hi>onely.</hi>)</p>
            <p>But it may, and certainly doth many times befal them, to finde and feel the inward power and demonſtration of the Spirit inviſibly and inwardly, whenas they are deprived of the external Manifeſtations of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.15, 16, 17: when the ſoul cannot, and what it cannot ſee, it may by the inward power of the Spirit believe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. when it cannot poſſeſs and enjoy, it may by the power of the ſame Spirit be helped to wait for, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24, 25. and when it knows not what to pray for as it ought, it may by the inward power of the ſame Spirit be enabled to ſigh and groan to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:171394:28"/>This did ſeeme to be the condition of thoſe believers in the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> who though they believed through the inward power of the Spirit upon their hearts, yet they were ignorant of the external power and demonſtration of the Spirit; and conſequently, what they were further to know and do <hi>Act.</hi> 19.2, 6. <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who though the power of the Spirit had been great upon his heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.24, yet he was ignorant of that external demonſtration, and power which afterwards he received, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Paul,</hi> though it pleaſed God to reveale himſelf to him, or in him, in the way, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16, and cauſed him to pray in or by the Spirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.11, compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26 27; yet he remained ignorant of that external power and demonſtration of the Spirit, which afterward he received, when <hi>Ananias</hi> came unto him, and laid his hands upon him and opened his eyes, and told him what he ſhould do, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6, 17.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the Word, or the Apoſtles Miniſtery, came both in word and power; both in the outward demonſtration, and inward operation: and then it made men obedient in word and deed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16, 19. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4 5.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I conceive I may ſay in anſwer to your Queſtion,</p>
            <p>That the word of the Goſpel, or Miniſtery of the Apoſtles, (as you call it) is ſo far forth efficacious to put the Saints upon doing their duties, as it comes furniſhed with the demonſtration and power of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>If the Spirit do demonſtrate, and make evident to the Soule that part of the Word which concerns the Soul's hope, faith, joy, love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according as that Word is evidenced with demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and power of the Spirit to the Soule, ſo far is that Soule not onely taught, but enabled to hope, believe, joy, love; and no farther.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe for that part of the Word which requires outward obedience; ſo far as the demonſtration and power of the Spirit comes, ſo far are we taught and enabled outwardly to obey. Now the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit is (as I conceive) the Spirits evidencing and making manifeſt the true intent and minde of the Apoſtles in the Miniſtery, as it did evidence and make manifeſt its own minde in their Adminiſtrations, when they did adminiſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:171394:29"/>Now the Apoſtles they ſpake by the Spirit, and had the minde of Chriſt. He therefore that will interpret their minde in their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which was none other but the minde of Chriſt, muſt do it by the power, demonſtration, and evidence of the ſame Spirit by which they ſpake, which was unerring and infallible. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11, 12, 16, <hi>Who knows the minde of a man, but the ſpirit of a man?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, though it might be ſuppoſed that there were a clear demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit, yet, without the power of the ſame Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers were not ſufficiently furniſhed to obedience, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45, 49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38.</p>
            <p>This Power I take to be a power of Authority, as well as Ability, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18; and this Authority and Ability are both required, at leaſt in ſome of the branches of a believers obedience.</p>
            <p>In particular, the buſineſs of the Miniſtery and the Adminiſtrations which are particular to a Church (I conceive) are ſuch as unto which there is required, in whomſoever they may concern, a clear under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the Spirit, ſo as to be able to ſay, <hi>I have the minde of</hi> Chriſt, and, <hi>Thus ſpeaks the Lord, and not I.</hi> A true Power of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as well as Ability, to do that work which they ſay (by the Spirit) is their duty to do, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45 49. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.6, 8. A clear evidence and manifeſtation thereof, not onely in themſelves, but to manifeſt to others, for their profit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>Now if there be ſuch Believers, who not onely touching their own perſonal eſtate and condition, but alſo touching Viſible Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of Publike Worſhip, can ſay in truth, by the Spirit, <hi>We have the minde of Chriſt,</hi> and, <hi>This ſpeaks the Lord, and not we;</hi> and have alſo a true and lawful authority to act thoſe things they ſay they know; I ſhall leave ſuch perſons to the trial of their ſpirits, and not doubt but to be able to ſee that ſpirit demonſtrating it ſelf to the world, either in them or others, to the praiſe and glory of the God and Father of ſpirits.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, I ſhall conceive, that whatſoever in the Word is required of believers to do perſonally, as believers, that ought to be endeavoured after by every one that is truely ſo: But whatſoever is relatively appropriated to perſons, as ſuch and ſuch, due regard is to be had to God's Order and Diſpenſation there, according to the limits and bounds he hath ſet. Better it is to be fed of Ravens, or faſt fourty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171394:29"/>
days, then, diſtruſting God's proviſion, turn ſtones into bread. Read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.11, 12, 13, a fair pretence: <hi>but he that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth maketh not haſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether thoſe Signes and Wonders whereby God manifeſted his preſence with the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> were not rather to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Word and Doctrine, then to bear witneſs to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being ſent, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is, in my underſtanding, a truth,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that thoſe Signes and Wonders were to confirm their Word and Doctrine, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.20. but the caſe is evident, that the works which God wrought by them, were not onely to confirm their Word, but alſo to teſtifie of their Perſons, that they were ſent of God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.36, <hi>The works which the Father hath given me to finiſh, the ſame works that I do, bear witneſs of me, that the Father hath ſent me:</hi> compared with <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, <hi>As my Father ſent forth me, ſo I ſend forth you,</hi> Joh. 17.18.</p>
            <p>If the Father ſent forth Chriſt, and the works which Chriſt did teſtified of him, that he was ſent of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.42; then Chriſt ſending forth his Diſciples, as the Father ſent forth him, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.13, 14, 16, the works which they do, teſtifie of them, that they are ſent of Chriſt; as the works which he did, teſtified of him, that he was ſent of God. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, <hi>The ſignes of an Apoſtle were wrought among you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Seeing gifts are <hi>given to profit withal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> and talents to be improved; How, according to Rule and Order, may the Saints edifie one another, and improve their talents for the honour of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, out of a Church-eſtate? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as the gifts and talents be which are given,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> ſuch muſt the improvement of them be for the honour of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I pray you conſider the Scripture you have quoted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Where thoſe gifts of the Spirit which are there ſpoken of are to be found, there need not be any care taken how to improve them, out of a Church: for ſurely then and there will be a glorious Church, where and when thoſe gifts of the Spirit are given to profit with. Where there is given by the Spirit, a word of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, a word of Knowledge, a gift of Faith, a gift of Healing, a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171394:30"/>
gift of Miracles, a gift of Prophecie, a gift of diſcerning of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, a gift of Tongues, and Interpretation of Tongues; when <hi>the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every one to profit withal,</hi> as the Scripture expreſſeth; then there will be an Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Adminiſtration, and an Effectual Operation, to the honour of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, I could deſire the Lord's people to conſider of that thing they call <hi>Gift,</hi> or <hi>Gifts,</hi> and try by what Name or Title they may be diſtinguiſhed or called; Whether any of theſe before mentioned, or ſome other. If not theſe, but ſome other, I would conſider what it is, Whether it be given to them to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> Phil. 1.29. to hope, joy, ſuffer, pray, to diſtribute to the Lord's poor, to bear the burden of the afflicted, to mourn over the deſolations of <hi>the Iſrael of God,</hi> to wait for the Day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, to long, to groan, in expectation for the Day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>gifts</hi> you ſpeak of be of the firſt kinde mentioned in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. they bring manifeſtation enough with them, to direct to the improvement of them; and where-ever they are found, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Church of Chriſt is not far off.</p>
            <p>If they be of the later ſort, I conceive the Spirit of the Lord (whoſe gifts they are) is not wanting, to manifeſt to ſuch to whom they are given, how they in their meaſure may be improved to the glory of him that is the author of them.</p>
            <p>But yet a few words more particularly, to what I conceive may be the ſcope of the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle (in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6, 11.) ſpeaking of the Jews, and that which befel them, ſaith, <hi>Thoſe things happened to them in types;</hi> and, <hi>Whatſoever was written before-time, was written for our learning.</hi> Now it is to be noted, that in their travelling condition, while they were in the wilderneſs, they were our Types, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. In their Temple-ſtate, they were our Types; and what God ſpake to them then, was as typing out the ſtate which was to come after, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. In the ſtate of their Captivity, they were the types of the Captivity of the preſent <hi>Iſrael of God, Jer.</hi> 50. <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.2, 4.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171394:30"/>
Therefore, what is recorded of them, and what befel them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Divine wiſdom of the moſt holy God, is written for us, and for our learning, that we might fear with a holy fear.</p>
            <p>Now it appears, by the teſtimony of Divine Truth, that there were ſome parts of Worſhip which the people were to perform to their God in the Temple at Jeruſalem, and not elſewhere, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.6, 7, 11, 13, 14. But there were ſome other parts of his Worſhip which they might perform to him when they were at the greateſt diſtance from the Temple, even in the Land of their Captivity. When they were in their own Land, they were to perform their Temple-work and Temple-worſhip at Jeruſalem, the place where God had choſen to put his Name: But in caſe the Lord ſhould deliver them into the hands of their enemies, and they ſhould be led captive into a ſtrange Land; inaſmuch as they could not come to Jeruſalem to worſhip before the Lord there, yet if they did but <hi>remember</hi> the Lord <hi>in the land of their captivity,</hi> and did <hi>humble themſelves, and pray</hi> unto him <hi>looking towards his houſe,</hi> he would <hi>hear in heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That the Lord's Iſrael might be put paſt Temple-work and worſhip, read 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.44, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51. and yet in this their condition, when they could not come to Jeruſalem, if they did but look towards it, and repent, and pray, God would have mercy, hear, and forgive.</p>
            <p>That theſe people were carried captive, appears, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.17, to the end of verſ. 21. Now the Sion of God became a <hi>plowed field.</hi> Now the ways of Sion mourned: none came to her ſolemn Aſſemblies; and, for their part, they could not ſing the ſongs of Jehovah in a ſtrange Land. Now the Lord had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his two ſtaves of Beauty and Bands, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.9, 10, 14. Now was <hi>Iſrael</hi> given up to the Robbers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.23, 24, 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Well:<note place="margin">Queſt,</note> but what do theſe people do in the Land of their Captivity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They ſeek the Lord by Faſting and Prayer,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Houſe; they hang their Harps upon the willows, and fall a mourning and weeping at the remembrance of Sion. Read theſe Scriptures: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.2, 3, 4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.3, 5. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.19, 21, 22. <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.23.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171394:31"/>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But did the people ever pray together, during the time of their Captivity?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea: beſides what other places of Scripture may hold out for the clearing of it, without doubt it lies clear in the face of this Text, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.3, 16. <hi>Go, [gather together] all the Jews which are in Shuſhan, and faſt ye for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever this were the caſe of this people, and they were herein, as well as in other things, Types in reſpect of what was to come, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks we are taught to conſider that which was afore-time written for our learning, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. That in the Chriſtian Church-ſtate there is ſomething ſo peculiar to it, as that it may not elſewhere be adminiſtred; as the power of Binding and Looſing in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, together with the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of ſuch Ordinances as are peculiar to a Church; wherein the Primitive Churches were exerciſed for their ſeaſon, contending <hi>earneſtly for the faith once given to the Saints;</hi> the woman wearing her Brides attire, her goodly cloathing, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. until the Dragon made war againſt her, and put her to flight, purſuing her with floods of water; in which condition of hers, ſhe hath lien in the wilderneſs of the world, in the rubbiſh and confuſion of Babel, <hi>among the pots,</hi> unpoliſhed, growing up as <hi>a lily among thorns,</hi> here one, and there another, like an Army routed, like Sheep unfolded, according to that Scripture, <hi>I ſaw all Iſrael ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon the mountains, like ſheep having no ſhepherd,</hi> 1 King. 22.17.</p>
            <p>Oh that we could read with affection thoſe paſſages, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81. Oh how is the <hi>Sion</hi> of the Lord <hi>become a plowed field</hi> indeed! How is the <hi>Vineyard</hi> of the Lord <hi>ſpoiled!</hi> Once it was not ſo: but, at this day, how do the poor people of the Lord rend, and devour, and tear, and eat up one another! what ſharp and bitter words! How great is <hi>the company of ſpear-men!</hi> the mother eating up the children of a ſpan long. Could this be, if the Veil were taken away, and our Bondage removed? What may be the reaſon Truth is ſo miſcalled, ſo miſtaken? (one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to have it, and another to have it:) Is it not becauſe <hi>night is to us for a viſion?</hi> We ſay we ſee, and we think we ſee; but know not that we are as men that dream. The Builders are at
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171394:31"/>
oddes among themſelves, and the ſtones in the building riſe up one againſt another. Can Chriſt be thus divided? If that his true Miniſtery were on foot, would not that rectifie that great Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is among the Builders? Would not a Trowel be a Trowel, and Brick be Brick, and Mortar be Mortar? Would not the language of Truth be diſtinctly underſtood? Would he ſuffer one of his own ſervants to throw down what another moſt dear to himſelf hath been a building up; and a third to deſtroy the work of them both? Oh how great is the deſolation, if we were but ſenſible of it, and affected with it! And when we think to mend our ſelves, and to become <hi>Repairers of the breaches,</hi> behold, <hi>in ſtead of a girdle, a rent; in ſtead of well-ſet hair, baldneſs.</hi> This, this is the condition of the Lord's people, to them that ſee it: and ſurely, <hi>unleſs the Lord of hoſts had left us a remnant, we had been like Sodom.</hi> But bleſſed be the Lord our Rock, who hath given us <hi>the valley of Achor for a door of hope,</hi> Hoſ. 2.15. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.16, 17. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8, 9, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Now the condition of the Lords Iſrael being thus routed, thus ſcattered; they ought to be afflicted deeply with this their deſolation and ſcattering; yet not to mourn as men without hope, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.15, 16, 17, but <hi>cry mightily unto the Lord, and give him no reſt,</hi> Iſa. 62.1, 6, 7. Luk. 18.1, 7, 8. <hi>To beare one anothers burthens; To inquire of the Lord,</hi> and one of another, <hi>the way to Sion,</hi> Jer. 50.4, 5, 6. <hi>To inquire after the true Lord Jeſus,</hi> Cant. 6.1. Thus, according to this order and pattern of a poor captivated people, ought the ſcattered Iſrael of Jehovah to go mourning, and weeping, and ſeeking the Lord: and not to go about to build, and ſet up wayes, by their own miſtaken, miſcalled, and miſunderſtood gifts: But to wait upon the Lord, leſt it be to them <hi>in ſtead of a girdle, a rent,</hi> Iſa. 3.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Seeing God hath promiſed,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
               <hi>That from the riſing of the Sun to the going down of the ſame, his Name ſhall be great among the Gentiles,</hi> Mal. 1.11; How ſhall this Name of Chriſt be proclaimed, and made great among the Gentiles, in this deſolate and loſt condition? according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Queſtion ſeems to be like <hi>Iſaac's</hi> Queſtion to his<note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:171394:32"/>
Father; <hi>My Father, where is the Lamb for the Sacrifice?</hi> and the Anſwer may be the ſame that his was to his Son, <hi>God will provide himſelf a Lamb.</hi> I would intreate you to read theſe Scriptures, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.7, 10. <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4. the whole Chapter; and that paſſage mentioned in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15, being compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.7, doth evidently declare, that there is yet a further ſending forth of the Meſſengers of Peace; when the Sion of God ſhall awake and put on ſtrength, and Jeruſalem the holy City ſhall put on beautiful garments. Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and judge whether this be not a Goſpel-Prophecie, part whereof is yet unfulfilled. And whether this be not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſcope, in the tenth of the <hi>Romans, verſ.</hi> 14, 15, and the whole eleventh <hi>Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi> Onely while you ſay, How ſhall this be? The wiſdome of Jehovah can bring this about, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 12, 13, 14. When the time of the Lord is come, wherein that great Angel ſhall lighten the earth with his glory, <hi>Rev</hi> 18.1, and wherein the Angel ſhall flie in the midſt of Heaven, having the ancient Goſpel to preach to them that dwell on the earth, to every nation, kindred, and tongue, and People, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. When the Lord of the Harveſt ſeeing the fields white to the Harveſt, ſhall thruſt forth labourers into his Harveſt: when his Angels or Meſſengers ſhall be ſent forth to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his elect from the four winds, from one end of Heaven to the other, <hi>The zeal of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall perform this,</hi> though we know not how.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If there be not a Miniſtery in the World, What will become of the Faith of all ſuch as believe in the Lord Jeſus, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferenced and diſhinguiſhed under thoſe ſeveral profeſſions, and known by thoſe ſeveral appellations whereby men have named them;<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> ſeeing the Scripture witneſſeth, that men cannot believe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Preacher? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.41.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection grounds it ſelf upon an abſurdity that will ſeem to follow upon the premiſes; <hi>viz.</hi> If what hath been alleadged, be true, touching the Miniſtery, How can this Scripture be true alſo, which ſaith, <hi>How can they believe on him of whom they have not heard? And how ſhall they hear without a Preacher?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:171394:32"/>To ſolve which ſeeming-contradiction, I deſire the Reader to conſider who that relative word <hi>they</hi> muſt be applied to: And conſequently, what is the ſcope of the Apoſtles argument in this place.</p>
            <p>For the underſtanding of which, I conceive it will be neceſſary to read the ninth, tenth, and eleventh Chapters together, and they will appear to be one continued Diſcourſe or Argument, whereby the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth hold forth the ſtate of the Jewes, (whom he calls his <hi>brethren,</hi> his <hi>kinſmen according to the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 9.3.</p>
            <p>Now concerning theſe, he begins all the three Chapters, and ſhewes both their priviledges which they had by the Law, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Their rejection, through their non-ſubmiſſion to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>Their reſtitution when the fulneſs of the Gentiles is come, in <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.25, to fulfil the Myſtery of this diſpenſation of God, by the appearing of the deliverer, who <hi>ſhall turn away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs from Jacob,</hi> according to his Covenant, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25, 26, 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.20, 21.</p>
            <p>Theſe are that <hi>they</hi> which are mentioned in the 1, 2, 3, and 14 <hi>Verſes</hi> of the tenth <hi>Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Romans;</hi> touching whom, the Apoſtle thus reaſons:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they might be ſaved. For I hear them record,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But, bleſſed Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Object.</note> what ground of Faith is there in this prayer, conſidering how they are rejected?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture hath ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever believeth in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not be aſhamed: for there is no difference between the Iew and the Greek; for the ſame Lord over all, is rich unto all that call upon him: For whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Therefore <hi>they, viz.</hi> the Jews, if <hi>they call upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> they <hi>ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely the Queſtion is, <hi>How</hi> they <hi>ſhall call upon him in whom</hi> they <hi>have not believed? and how ſhall</hi> they <hi>believe in him of whom</hi> they <hi>have not heard? and how ſhall</hi> they <hi>hear without out a Preacher? and how ſhall</hi> they <hi>Preach except</hi> they <hi>be ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:171394:33"/>Therefore, till there be a ſending forth of Meſſengers, even to the Jews, <hi>quatenus</hi> Jews, as well as there hath been to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>quâ</hi> ſuch, no wonder if <hi>they</hi> believe not: For, <hi>how can</hi> they <hi>believe in him of whom</hi> they <hi>have not heard? and how can</hi> they <hi>hear without a Preacher? and how can</hi> they <hi>Preach ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> they <hi>be ſent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But they have heard, though they have not obeyed; as appears,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16, 18, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This may not be denied: for, Chriſt was ſent firſt <hi>to the lost ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael; And he</hi> accordingly <hi>came unto his own, and his own received him not.</hi> But the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, makes the Myſtery the greater.</p>
            <p>Once God choſe the family of <hi>Abraham</hi> before all the families of the earth, <hi>and in Judah was God known, and his Name fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Iſrael. He dealt not ſo with any other nation, neither had they the knowledge of his Law.</hi> Though afterwards, when the fulneſs of time was come, and the wall of partition broken down by the appearing of our Lord Jeſus, then the Myſtery of Chriſt which in other ages was not made manifeſt, was revealed to his holy Apoſtles and Prophets,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.5, 6</note> by the Spirit; which Myſtery was, <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-heirs, and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Jewes, to whom the Goſpel firſt was preached, having put it from them, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi> and reckoned themſelves unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that ſalvation, became the onely nation of all the world, who were by the juſt hand of God concluded under blindneſs, and hardneſs, (in part) and ſo are to continue ſuch a proportion of time as was fore-appointed and decreed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8, 9, 10, 25. At the expiration and determination of which time, there is to be a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Myſtery of their breaking off, and ingrafting in again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and that to be done when <hi>the deliverer ſhall come out of Sion, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as in times paſt the Gentiles believed not, having not that opportunity of the knowledge of God as the Jews had; yet at length obtained mercy, through their unbelief: Even ſo have <hi>theſe</hi> alſo now not believed, that through their mercy <hi>they</hi> might obtain mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:171394:33"/>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how is this to be effected?<note place="margin">Object.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By means of the preaching of thoſe whom God in his holy and bleſſed time will ſend out for this work: For,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>how ſhall</hi> they <hi>call on him of whom</hi> they <hi>have not heard?</hi> (as the natural Jews have not, though their forefathers ſome of them did, and for their diſobedience were rejected.) <hi>And how ſhall they hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a preacher? and how ſhall they preach except they be ſent? As it is written, How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of them which preach the Goſpel!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which paſſage of Scripture, however it hath been applied to that publication of the Goſpel which hath had its courſe among the Gentiles, yet the Apoſtle here makes a ſpecial application thereof to the ſending forth of that Miniſtery which is to accompliſh this work; foraſmuch as that which is to accompany its adminiſtration, is ſomething which hath not as yet been performed, and which hath a peculiar fulfilling in the Calling of the Jews; as almoſt the whole Chapter from whence the Apoſtle fetcheth this paſſage, will evince, if the Scripture it ſelf be examined, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.7. Read verſ. 1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Well might the Apoſtle therefore ſay,<note place="margin">Iſa. 25.7.</note> 
               <hi>How can they hear without a preacher?</hi> foraſmuch as the time neither then was, nor appears yet to be come, wherein thoſe Meſſengers that are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bring them that <hi>glad tidings,</hi> after their long Captivity in blindneſs and hardneſs, under which they for a time were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, to fulfil the Word of the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But when the full time is accompliſhed, and that the <hi>Deliverer is come</hi> (to Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or <hi>out of Sion;</hi> Oh then <hi>how beautiful upon the mountains</hi> will be <hi>the feet of</hi> the Apoſtles or Meſſengers to whom ſhall be revealed this Myſtery, which hath been ſo long hid, but ſhall then be made manifeſt; and by whom the glad tidings thereof ſhall be publiſhed among thoſe, who, till this time, have not heard thereof, and conſequently could not believe!</p>
            <p>Not as if no man, Jew or Gentile, could hear of God and Chriſt, and things of heaven, ſo as to believe to ſalvation, without a ſpecial ſending of ſome perſon or perſons to preach unto them as a Miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> an Apoſtle, Prophet, or Paſtor; but that it could not be expected that the Nation of the Jews, who through their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171394:34"/>
unbelief had been broken off, that <hi>they</hi> ſhould be reſtored again, and become one ſheepfold with the Gentiles through believing; and the Myſtery hereof, be accompliſhed and revealed without a Preacher, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe Meſſengers whoſe feet were to be beautiful in publiſhing the glad tidings thereof, and which ſhould have its accompliſhment in its ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, And that this may the more manifeſtly appear to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to a ſpecial ſending of ſuch as hath been ſpoken of, the phraſe of ſpeech uſed in the fifteenth Verſe of the tenth Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> may ſomewhat help to evince.</p>
            <p>Where it may be obſerved, that the two eſpecial phraſes of ſpeech which import</p>
            <p>Authoritative
<list>
                  <item>Sending, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
                  <item>Preaching, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
               </list>
are uſed both for the ſending and preaching of thoſe Meſſengers which are there mentioned by the Apoſtle: whereas it will be found in the Scripture, that in the days of the firſt Miniſtery (when it was on foot in the world) that Faith was not ſo tied to a Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or to one ſo eſpecially ſent, (as this Scripture holds forth ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the terms of it) as that the Faith could not be true, where the Preaching and Sending was not ſuch, <hi>i. e.</hi> Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of <hi>Cornelius</hi> that devout Souldier, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the <hi>Italian band,</hi> of whom the bleſſed Witneſs of Truth teſtifies, <hi>That he feared God with all his houſe, and gave alms to the people, and prayed to God alwayes;</hi> whoſe prayers and alms (the Angel teſtifieth) were <hi>come up for a memorial before God.</hi> Now <hi>God heareth not ſinners,</hi> Joh. 9.31. And in the ninth of the <hi>Acts</hi> it's noted of <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had ſeen the Lord in the way, in the eleventh <hi>verſ. Behold he prayeth;</hi> which was an evidence of his converſion. Yet this <hi>Cornelius</hi> did, before any Miniſtery (that we read of) had made known the minde of the Lord unto him; as afterward it did in the concluſion of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But I refer this to the exerciſe of a free minde to conſider of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Friendly and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</note>There be other caſes beſides this of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> which may give light to this thing.</p>
            <p>The Faith of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who believed upon the report of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171394:34"/>
the woman communicating to them her experiences touching the Meſſiah, owns it ſelf to no ſuch Miniſtery as the Objection im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and holds forth, as the ſtory will eaſily make appear when it is read, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. the Lord Jeſus having ſpoken to her heart and ſhewed her the corruption thereof, in telling her ſhe had had five husbands, and he whom ſhe now had was not her husband, (a thing which ſhe knew very well already) this extorts from her an acknowledgment that he was a Prophet, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. but more begot more; in concluſion, ſhe left the water-pot, and went into the City, and communicated her experience to the people thereof, (men and women) <hi>Come, ſee a man that told me all that ever I did: Is not this the Chriſt?</hi> The effect of which declaration of hers was ſuch, as it not onely (if at all) prevailed with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that City to come to him, that by ſeeing him they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; but to believe, and ſo come to ſee: as themſelves teſtifie, <hi>Verſe</hi> 39, 40, 41, 42.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle mentions, as another meanes of converſion,</p>
            <p>A gratious Converſation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.16,<note place="margin">A holy and chaſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</note> compared with the firſt of <hi>Peter</hi> 3.1, <hi>For what knoweſt thou, O Wife, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy husband? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. —Convertes ad fidem Chriſtianam.</hi> It is the ſame word which is uſed in <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21, <hi>Salvabit populum ſuum à peccatis eorum: He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi> Which ſaving of the husband by the wife, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, 2, appropriates (inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally) to her <hi>chaſte converſation. Likewiſe, ye wives, be in ſubjection to your own husbands, that if any obey not the Word, they alſo may without the Word be won by the converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wives; while they behold your chaſt converſation with feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have obſerved touching the converſion of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Immediate Revelation</note> that it was effected by immediate revelation, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6, 11, compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.3. And though the Lord Jeſus preacht unto him in the way, yet he did it by himſelf, without ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as at that time he had appointed and placed in the world for the working Faith and Converſion.</p>
            <p>By all which it appeares, that however it is our duty to attend to ſuch means as God hath appointed, when and where they way be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171394:35"/>
injoyed; yet himſelf is not bound ſo to work by them, as that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work beſides them, and without them, when he pleaſeth; or that the Faith or Converſion which ownes not ſuch a Miniſtery to have a ſhare in it's working, muſt therefore not be true, becauſe not ſo wrought or effected as the Objection holds it forth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diligent ſearching the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note>To what hath been ſpoken, might be added the conſideration of the Faith of thoſe men of <hi>Berea, Act.</hi> 17.11, 12, which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes very much to their daily <hi>ſearching the Scriptures, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the things they heard of Paul and Silas were ſo;</hi> (and it's ſaid) <hi>Therefore many of them believed.</hi> No doubt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> preached to theſe, as they had before to thoſe of <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Verſ.</hi> 3, <hi>But theſe were more noble then the former, in that they ſearched the Scriptures</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> urged, to ſee <hi>whether the thing</hi> alleadged <hi>were ſo: therefore many of them believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the evangelizing of the ſcattered brethren, and the bleſſed ſucceſſe that enſued thereupon: who though they were ſo far from being Miniſterially ſent out, that they were ſent after, by the Churches at Jeruſalem, when tidings had come to their eares how the hand of the Lord was with them, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21, 22; yet their labour of Love and work in that particular was accepted, <hi>and many were turned to the Lord thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which it doth appear, that although <hi>Faith came by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God;</hi> yet it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that Faith cannot be true, or that none can be ſaid to believe who have not ſo heard, <hi>viz.</hi> By ſuch a preaching and ſending as that Scripture in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15, holds forth, and as this Objection would enforce: But on the contrary, rather, that although the Lord Jeſus did inſtitute and appoint ſome certaine perſons, choſen and deputed to the work of the Miniſtery, for the ends, and during the time mentioned in the fourth of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> to which men were to give attendance, as to the meanes appointed of God for thoſe ends; yet he was not bound ſo to work by thoſe inſtruments, and by none other, as if that whatſoever he wrought otherwiſe, or by other meanes, muſt be invalidated, becauſe it was not ſo effected; as the inſtances before alleadged, will with clearneſs, and no leſs comfort, evince.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:171394:35"/>Therefore this conſideration now preſented, will be ſo far from weakning, that it will adde much comfort and ſtrength to the Faith of the mourners of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the waiters for the hope of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> while they behold, that the moſt High hath placed ſuch footſteps amongſt his bleſſed Oracles of Truth (the Scriptures) that may ſtay from wandering, and preſerve from fainting their wearied Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in other things, ſo alſo in this, <hi>that their Faith and Hope may be found in God,</hi> and they no way enforced to build upon the wiſdome of men, that would be eſteemed the Miniſters and Meſſengers of Chriſt, in ſtead of thoſe that once were ſo.</p>
            <p>And may ſerve as a good help, till better do appear, to free the minde and ſpirit of ſome that are ſincere, from that Bull or Comination which hath taken hold of them; enforcing it ſelf upon the Conſcience, not to dare to queſtion the preſent Miniſtery, leſt they be neceſſitated to queſtion their own Faith alſo; though this queſtioning extends it ſelf no farther, then to try it by the rules of the Word; a thing ſo frequently commanded by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And the impartial exerciſe whereof, though it might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with ſome to ſee their preſent loſs, and that they are not what they have taken themſelves to be, and abate much of the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence which moſt men have; yet would it not at all take off the ground of their conſolation, nor the exerciſe of their gratious abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in ſearching the Scriptures as touching the preſent Truth, as the men of <hi>Berea</hi> did; nor of communicating their gratious experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as that good woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> did, or thoſe honeſt-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed brethren of the diſperſion; nor of holding forth a holy, harmleſs, and chaſte Converſation, winning and inſtrumentally ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe who poſſibly may not be won by the Word; themſelves mean while being found faithful witneſſes to Truth, ſo far as they have attained, and waiters for that grace which is to be brought at the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:171394:36"/>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Now the Lord direct our hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the love of God, and into a patient waiting for Christ; foraſmuch as unto them that look for him, ſhall he appear the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: therefore in patience, let us poſſeſs our ſouls, knowing that the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea haſtning, wherein the blinde ſhall ſee, the lame ſhall leap, and the ſtamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tongue be unlooſed. In the mean time,</hi>
               <q>Let Brotherly love continue.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171394:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
